<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A very excelle[n]t [and] swete exposition vpon the XXII. [sic] Psalme of Dauid called in Latine Dominus regit me, &amp;c. Translated out of hye Almayne into Englyshe by Myles Couerdale.</title>
            <title>Dreiundzwanzigste Psalm der Tisch ausgelegt. English</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104352</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840090</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840090</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06532)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 136:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A very excelle[n]t [and] swete exposition vpon the XXII. [sic] Psalme of Dauid called in Latine Dominus regit me, &amp;c. Translated out of hye Almayne into Englyshe by Myles Couerdale.</title>
                  <title>Dreiundzwanzigste Psalm der Tisch ausgelegt. English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Coverdale, Miles, 1488-1568. aut</author>
                  <author>Osiander, Andreas, 1498-1552. Wie und wohin ein Christ die grausamen Plag der Pestilentz fliehen soll. English. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By me James Nicolson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed in Southwarke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno MDXXXVIII. [1538]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Miles Coverdale, of: Luther, Martin. Der dreiundzwanzigste Psalm der Tisch ausgelegt.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication, and printer's and publisher's names from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Includes a translation, by Miles Coverdale, of Andreas Osiander's "Wie und wohin ein Christ die grausamen Plag der Pestilentz fliehen soll", which has a separate title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An exposition upon the. xxii. Psalme.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:1"/>
                  <p>A very excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſwete expoſition vpon the XXII. Pſalme of Dauid called in Latine:</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Dominus regit me, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>¶ Tranſlated oute of Hye Almayne into Englyſhe by Myles Couerdale.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno MDXXXVIII.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="Psalm">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:2"/>
                  <head>The .xxii. pſalme of Dauid called in Latine Dominus regit me, et nihil</head>
                  <p>i The <hi>LORDE</hi> is my ſhepeherde, I ſhall lacke nothynge.</p>
                  <p>ii He fedeth me in a grene paſture, and leadeth me to the freſh water.</p>
                  <p>iii He quyckeneth my ſoule, and brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth me forth in the waye of ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, for hys names ſake.</p>
                  <p>iiii Though I walke in the valley of the ſhadowe of death, yet feare I no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for thou arte wyth me: Thy ſtaffe and thy ſhepehooke do comforte me</p>
                  <p>v Thou prepareſt a table before me agaynſte myne enemyes, thou anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſte my head wyth oyle, and fylleſt my cuppe full.</p>
                  <p>vi Oh let thy louynge kyndneſſe and mercye followe me all the dayes of my lyfe, that I maye dwell in the houſe of the <hi>LORD</hi> for euer.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:2"/>
                  <head>¶ An expoſition vpon the .xxii. Pſalme.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The effect of this Pſalme</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Pſalme doth Dauid and euery chriſten hart geue thankes &amp; prayſe vnto God for his moſt principal benefit, namely, for the preachyng of his dear &amp; holy word, wherby we are called, accepted, and no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred amonge the multitude, which is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion or church of God: where onely (and in no pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce els) the pure doctrine, the true knowlege of Gods wyll, and the ryght ſeruice of God is founde and had.</p>
                  <p>But this ſame noble treaſure doth holy Dauid prayſe and extol maruaylous excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently with goodly, ſwete, fayre, &amp; pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, yee &amp; that with lykeneſſes, borowed out of the Gods ſeruice of the olde Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>Fyrſt, he lykeneth hymſelfe to a ſhepe, whom God hymſelfe (as a faythfull diligent ſhepherde) doth wonderous well take hede vnto,<note place="margin">A ſhepe</note> fedeth hym in a pleaſaunt grene paſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, whiche ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth full of good thicke graſſe, where ther is abundaunce alſo of freſhe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; no ſcarceneſſe. Item he lykeneth God alſo vnto ſuche a ſhepherde,<note place="margin">The ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herde</note> as with his ſtaf leadeth &amp; bryngeth the ſhepe the playne right way, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not go amyſſe, and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth
<pb facs="tcp:4561:3"/>hys flocke ſo wyth the ſhepehooke, that the woolfe can not break in. After thys doth he make hymſelfe a geſte,<note place="margin">A geſte</note> for whom God prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth a table, where he fyndeth both ſtrength and comforte, refreſhynge and ioye, and that plenteouſly.</p>
                  <p>And thus the Prophete geueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God diuerſe names,<note place="margin">The word of God hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny names.</note> calleth it goodly plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt grene graſſe, freſhe water, the ryght waye, a ſtaffe, a ſhephooke, a table, balme or pleaſaunt oyle, and a cuppe that is alwaye full. And thys he doth not without a cauſe: for the power of Gods worde is many folde For why? Lyke as a ſhepe in a fayre pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t medowe, beſyde the grene graſſe and freſhe water in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hys ſhepherde (which leadeth it wyth the ſtaffe or rodde, ſo that it can not go aſtraye: and defendeth it ſo with the ſhepehoke that no harme can happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it) hath hys foode &amp; pleaſure in al ſafegarde. Or lyke as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacketh nothynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſytteth at a table, where ther is plenty of meate and drynke, and al maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte &amp; gladneſſe: So muche more, they that be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepe of thys ſhepherd (wherof thys pſalme ſyngeth) lacke no good thynge, are rychely prouyded for, not only in ſoule but alſo in body. As Chriſt ſayeth in the ſixte of Mathew: Seke fyrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdome of God, and the ryghteouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4561:3"/>therof, ſo ſhal all theſe thynges be myniſtred vnto you. For as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wante bodely foode lyue in greate ſtraytneſſe and penſyfneſſe, not beynge able to fulfyl the bodyes requeſt in thys behalfe: euen ſo alſo thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wante thys wholſome and neceſſarye word of god, can not reioyce nor be pacyfyed inwardly. Yee euen as bread and wyne refreſh a mans fleſhy harte, and make hym ioyfull: euen ſo the worde of God quyckeneth &amp; refreſſheth a mans ſoule inwardly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge of gods wod bryngeth proſperite</note>For whan the worde of God is truly &amp; ſyncerely preached, loke how many dyuerſe names the prophete geueth it here, ſo many commodyties and frutes doth it brynge. Vnto them that are diligent and earneſt to heare it (whom oure LORDE God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely for hys owne ſhepe) it is a pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grene graſſe, a freſh water, wherewith they are ſatiſfyed and refreſhed. It kepeth them alſo in the ryghte waye, and preſerueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that no myſfortune nor harme happen vnto them. Moreouer, it is vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall wealth, where ther is abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunce of meate &amp; drynke, and all maner of ioye and pleaſure. That is, they are not onely inſtructe and gyded, refreſſhed, ſtrengthed and comforted by the worde of God, but euer more &amp; more preſerued in the ryght waye, defended in all
<pb facs="tcp:4561:4"/>maner of trouble both of body and ſoule. And fynally they haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory &amp; preuayle agaynſte all temptacyons and troubles, wherof they muſte abyde ryghte many, as the fourth verſe doth ſpecifye. Shortly, they lyue in all maner of ſafegarde, as they, vnto whome no myſfortune can happen, for as much as theyr ſhepherde doth fede them and preſerue them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne to be taken of this pſalm.</note>Therfore ſhulde we take inſtruccion out of thys Pſalme, not to deſpyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, but gladlye to heare, and learne the ſame, to loue it, and to make muche of it, &amp; to reſorte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lytle flock, where we maye haue it. And agayne on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſyde, to flye and eſchue thoſe that do blaſpheme and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it. For where thys bleſſed lyght doth not ſhyne, there is nother proſperite nor he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth, nother ſtrength, nor comforte, eyther in body or ſoule, but vtter dyſquietneſſe, ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>roure and diſpayre, ſpecially whan trouble, dyſtreſſe, and paynfull death is at hande. How be it the vngodly (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophete ſayeth) haue neuer reſt,<note place="margin">Eſaye. <hi>57.</hi>
                     </note> whether they be in welth or wo. For yf they be in proſperite, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they preſumptuous, proude, and hyghe mynded, forget oure LORDE god vtterly, boaſte, &amp; crake onely of theyr owne power, ryches, wyſdome, &amp;c. And take thought beſyde, how
<pb facs="tcp:4561:4"/>they maye maynteyn and increace the ſame, and how they may perſecute and oppreſſe other men that lye in theyr wayes. But yf the leafe turne aboute with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as doutleſſe it muſt nedes do at the laſt: (For that ſwete virgin Marye is a very ſure prophetiſſe,<note place="margin">Depoſuit pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes de ſede, &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes dimiſit inanes.</note> which yet hath not fayled in hyr ſonge) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they of all the mooſt miſerable &amp; careful leſt people, which immediatly fall to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpayre and miſtruſt. What ayleth them? They knowe not where nor how they ſhall ſeke comforte, ſeynge they haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, which onely teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght waye how to be pacient, and to haue a good hope, euen in aduerſite. Roma .xv. Thys thynge ought to warn vs &amp; moue vs, that we eſteme nothynge more excellent nor worthye vpon earth, than thys benefyte,<note place="margin">An enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for vs.</note> namely to haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deare bleſſed worde, and that we can be in a place, where it may be frelye preached, and profeſſed openlye. A Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> belongeth vnto a church, wherein the worde of god is taught, as oft as he goeth in, ſhuld thynke vpon thys Pſalme, &amp; out of a ioyfull harte wyth the prophete to geue God tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for hys vnoutſpeakable grace, that he hath ſet hym (as hys owne ſhepe) in a pleaſaunt grene medowe, where ther is plentye of good graſſe and freſh water. That is, that
<pb facs="tcp:4561:5"/>he maye be in a place where he maye heare &amp; learne the worde of God, &amp; conceaue ryche comforte therout, both in bodye, and ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Thys bleſſed Dauid dyd well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonde, how worthy a treaſure it is, whan it maye ſo be had, therfore can he boaſt &amp; ſinge ſo well of it, &amp; magnifyethys benefite aboue all that is in onye eſtymacion or worſhippe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth. At hym oughte we to learne thys ſcience,<note place="margin">What we ought to learne here of Dauid.</note> and (accordynge to hys enſample) not onely to be thankfull vnto God oure louynge and faythfull ſhepherde, &amp; to magni fye his vnout ſpeakeable gyft, which he of ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry louynge kyndneſſe hath geuen vs (as Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid doth here in the fyrſte fyue verſes,) but alſo earneſtly to deſyre and pray hym (as he doth in the laſt verſes,) that we maye abyde by thys ryches, and neuer to fal away from hys holy Chriſten churche.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch a prayer is exceadynge neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye: For we are very weake, and (as the Apoſtle ſaynt Paule ſayeth) we carye thys treaſure aboute in earthen veſſels.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell alſo our aduerſary beareth deadly hate vnto vs for thys treaſures ſake. Therfore doth he not reſt, but goeth aboute as a roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge Lyon, &amp; ſeketh how he maye deuoure vs. Beſyde all thys he hath a quarel vnto vs, becauſe of our olde ſacke which we carye
<pb facs="tcp:4561:5"/>yet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oure neckes, wherin ther be yet alſo dyuerſe concupiſcences and ſynnes. More ouer, the deare flocke of Chriſte is ſpotted &amp; fyled with ſo many horrible offences (or ſklau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders) that becauſe of the ſame ther do many fall awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore (I ſaye) it is neceſſary that we praye, and put thys vncorrupt doctryne ſtyll in practiſe, &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d oure ſelues therwith agaynſt all ſklau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, that we maye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; be ſaued.</p>
                  <p>Thys madde and blynde worlde kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vtterly nothynge of thys treaſure and precious ſtone,<note place="margin">The blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde.</note> but ymagyneth onely (euen as a ſwyne or vnreaſonable beaſt) how they maye here fyll the belly: Or els (whan it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the poynt) they follow lyes &amp; ypocri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye: As for the truthe and fayth, they ſet it paſſe. Therfore do they ſynge no Pſalme vnto God for hys holy worde, but rather (whan he offreth it vnto them) they blaſphe me it, and condemne it for hereſye. And as for thoſe that teache it, or wyl be knowen of it, the worlde perſecuteth them, and putteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death, lyke as yf they were deceauers, and the moſt vngracyous wretches y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in the worlde. It ſhalbe good therfore for thys ſmall flocke to knowlege ſuche a benefyte, &amp; wyth the prophete to ſynge a Pſalme or ſonge of thankeſgeuyng vnto God for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4561:6"/>
                     <note place="margin">Of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolde, and can not haue the worde of God.</note>But what ſaye ye of them that can not haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachynge of Gods worde? As na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, they that dwell here and there amonge tyrauntes and enemyes of the truthe? No doute, where as the worde of God is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, there can it not paſſe awaye wythout frute, as Eſay ſayeth in the .lv. Chap. The good chriſten people alſo of the ſame place haue one vauntage, which in dede is deare vnto them. For they that be Chriſten men, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te it a very great thynge, that they may be in a place where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God is frely and openly taught and knowleged, and the ſacramentes myniſtred after Chriſtes inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tucion. But as for theſe, they be ſowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very thynne. The falſe chriſten are alwaye mo then the good. The great multitude careth nothynge for Gods worde, nother do they knowlege it for a benefyte, that they may hear it without al harme &amp; parel. Yee they are ſoone fylled and weery of it, and eſteme it but a payne to heare it, and to receaue the holy ſacrament.</p>
                  <p>Agayne, they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffre vnder tyrauntes, complayne daye and nyght, and long great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for it. And yf a ſmal morſel of oure bread that Chriſte hath geuen vs ſo rychely doth come vnto them, they receaue it wyth great ioye and thankfulneſſe, and do them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:4561:6"/>muche good withall,<note place="margin">Men ware weery of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God.</note> where as oure ſwyne in the meane ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worthy bread them ſelues ſo rychely, and many whole baſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kettes full therof, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not reache vnto it, they are ſo weery of it. Yee they caſt it downe, walowe them ſelues therin, treade it vnder theyr fete, and runne ouer it.</p>
                  <p>Therfore goeth it eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouerbe. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thynge beginneth to be comune, it is nomore ſet by, but deſpyſed, be it neuer ſo precious. And ſuche Prouerbes are ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally founde true in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God. Where men haue it, there wyl they not away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Agayne, where men haue it not, there wolde they be gſad to haue it. Where men haue a church at theyr dores wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God is taught, there go they vp &amp; downe in the market in the preachynge tyme, and lurcke about the graues. Where they be ten or twentye myle from it, there wold they be glad to go with the multitude, and to paſſe ouer with them vnto the houſe of God with ioyfulneſſe, and thankeſgeuynge, as it is in the .xli. Pſalme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwelvnder tyrauntes.</note>Therfore ſhortelye thys is myne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto the queſtion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dwel vnder tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: Bleſſed be they which are now ſcattered abrode vnder the Turke or Pope, beynge deſritute of Gods worde, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4561:7"/>wolde yet be glad wyth all theyr hartes to haue it, &amp; in the meane ſeaſon receaue wyth thankeſgeuynge ſuche morſels as they can get, tyll the meale be better. Nowe yf they be not farre from the place where the worde of God is preached, and the bleſſed ſacrament mynyfired accordyng vnto Chriſtes inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucion, they maye well go thyther, &amp; enioye the ſame treaſure, lyke as many do, and are therfore punyſhed of theyr wycked rulers, both in body, and goodes. But yf they dwel farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche places, yet do they not ceaſſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leeſt to ſighe therafter. No doute Chriſt oure LORDE wyll heare theyr ſighynge, &amp; in proceſſe of tyme wyl he turne back theyr captyuyte. Agayne, vnhappye, yee and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie agayna are they, that haue this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure plenteouſlye at theyr dores, and yet care not for it. On them ſhall the word of Chriſt be fulfylled where he ſayeth.<note place="margin">Mathei. 8</note> Many ſhall come from the eaſte, and weſt, &amp; ſhall ſyt wyth Abraham, Iſaar, and Iacob in the kyngdome of heauen, but the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kyngdome ſhalbe caſt out. &amp;c. Let thys be ſayde for an introduccion. Nowe wyll we ſhortly go ouer the Pſalme.</p>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb facs="tcp:4561:7"/>
                     <head>¶ The <hi>LORDE</hi> is my ſhepherde, I ſhall lacke nothynge.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſt of all the prophet and euery faythfull hart, calleth God hys ſhepherde. Nowe though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture geueth God many louynge names, Yet thys whiche the Prophete ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth here vnto God, is a much more ſwete and gracyous name, where he calleth hym a ſhepherde, and ſayeth:<note place="margin">A ſwet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> name.</note>
                        <hi>The</hi> LORD <hi>is my ſhepherde.</hi> It is very comfortable whan the ſcripture calleth God our hope, oure ſtrength, oure ſtonye rocke, our caſtell, our ſhelde, our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, our deliuerer, our kynge. &amp;c. For verely he declareth the thynge ſo ſtyll in dede vnto his owne, that he is euen ſo as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture deſcribeth hym. But exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable is it that he is called here (and many tymes els in the ſcripture) a <hi>ſhepeherde.</hi> For in this only word <hi>Shepe herde,</hi> is almoſt all comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded together, what good and comfortable thynge ſo euer is ſpoken of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet to cal God his ſhey herds.</note>Therfore doth the prophete ſpeake thys worde wyth a ioyfull and ſorowleſſe hart, whych is full of fayth, and for very great gladneſſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, exceadeth. And ſayeth not: <hi>The</hi> LORDE <hi>is my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, caſtel.</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:4561:8"/>Whiche were a maruaylous comfortable ſayenge: But <hi>the</hi> LORD <hi>is my ſhepherde</hi> As yf he wolde ſay: Yf the LORDE be my ſhepherde, and I his ſhepe, then am I wonde rous well prouided for, both in body &amp; ſoule, he ſhall get me a competent lyuynge, he ſhall defende me &amp; kepe me fro myſfortune, he ſhal care for me, he ſhall helpe me out of all trou ble, he ſhall confort me, he ſhall ſtrength me. &amp;c. Summa, he ſhall do for me what ſo euer a good ſhepherde ought to do. All theſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites and mo doth he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in this onely worde Shepherde, as he expoundeth it hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe immediatly, where he ſayeth: <hi>I ſhall lacke nothynge.</hi> Beſydes this ſome of the other names which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture aſcribe vnto God, ſounde partly to glorious and to hye, &amp; brynge in a maner a feare with them, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be named. As wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calleth God our LORDE, Kynge, Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker. &amp;c. Of ſuch a nature is not this worde Shepherde, but ſoundeth very frendly, and vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be godly, it bryngeth in a maner a confidence, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte and truſt with it wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they reade or hear it, lyke as this worde Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, and other mo, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>y co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> le ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>de.</note>Therfore is this one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt louyng and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable ſimilitudes (&amp; yet very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>)
<pb facs="tcp:4561:8"/>in the ſcripture, that it lykeneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſty of god, to avertuous, faythful, or (as Chriſt ſayeth) a good ſhepherde: and vs poore, weake, and wretched ſynners to a ſhepe.</p>
                     <p>Now can not thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable &amp; louynge ſimilitude be better vnderſtande, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to go into the creatures themſelues (wherout the prophetes toke thys &amp; ſuch other lyke ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes,) and to learne diligently thereby, what the condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and property of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſhepe is, and the office, labour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of a good ſhepherde. Who ſo taketh good hede therunto, maye not onely wyth eaſe vnderſtande this and other ſimilitudes in the ſcripture concernynge the ſhepherde and the ſhepe: but alſo they ſhalbe vnto him exceadynge ſwete and comfortable.</p>
                     <p>A ſhepe muſt lyue only by the helpe, de fence and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hys ſhepherde:<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion of a ſhepe.</note> as ſoone as it leſeth hym, it is compaſſed about with all maner of parell, and muſt nedes peryſh: for it can not helpe it ſelfe. For why, it is a poore, weake and innocent beaſt, that can nother fede nor gyde it ſelfe, nor fynde the ryght waye, nor kepe it ſelfe agaynſt ony vnhappyneſſe or miſfortune. Sauynge this that of nature it is fearfull, flyeth &amp; goeth aſtraye. And yf it go but a lytle out of the waye, and come from hys ſhepherde, it is
<pb facs="tcp:4561:9"/>not poſſible for it ſelfe to fynde hym agayne, but runneth euer farther and farther from him And though it come to other ſhepherdes and ſhepe, yet is it nothynge helped ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. For it knoweth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſhepherdes, therfore flyeth it from them, and runneth ſo longe aſtraye, tyll the wolfe rauyſh it, or tyll it peryſh ſome other wayes.</p>
                     <p>Neuertheleſſe as weake a beaſte as it is, yet hath it thys condicion,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of a ſhepe.</note> that wyth all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it bydeth with his owne ſhepherde, and ſeketh comforte at hys helpe and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: And how or whether ſo euer he leadeth it, it followeth. And yf it can but be with hym, it careth for nomore, nother feareth it ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but is careleſſe and mery, for it lacketh nothynge. It hath alſo thys good vertue in it, whiche is well to be marked: (for Chriſt doth ſpecially prayſe the ſame in hys ſhepe) thys vertue, I ſaye, it hath, that it wyll be earneſt and ſure to heare and knowe the voyce of hys ſhepherde, and ordreth it ſelfe therafter, and wyl for nothynge go from it, but followeth ſtrayght the ſame. Agayne, it regardeth no ſtraunge ſhepherdes voyce. And though they call and whiſtle vppon it neuer ſo frendly, yet careth not it therfore: much leſſe doth it followe them.</p>
                     <p>Agayne,<note place="margin">The office of a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde.</note> this is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> office of a good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:9"/>that he doth not only prouyde for his ſhepe paſture, and other mo thynges that belonge therto, but defendeth them alſo that no harme chaunce vnto them. Beſydes this he taketh diligent hede that he lefe none. Yf ony go aſtraye, he runneth after it, ſeketh it, and fetcheth it agayne. As for ſuch as be yonge, feble, and ſicke, he dealeth gently w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, kepeth them, holdeth them vp, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tyll they be olde, ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; whole. &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Euen thus goeth it alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirituall ſhepfolde, that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">How it goeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhep folde of Chriſt.</note> in the flocke of Chriſt. Loke how lytle a naturall ſhepe can kepe, gyde, rule, ſaue or defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it ſelfe againſt daunger and myſfortune (for it is a feble and wapenleſſe beaſt:) So lytle ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we poore, weak, and miſerable people kepe &amp; rule our ſelues ſpiritually, walke and endure in the ryght waye, or of our owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs agaynſt all euel, and to get vs helpe and comforte in trouble and diſtreſſe.</p>
                     <p>For how ſhulde he haue ſkyll to gyde hym ſelfe after a godly faſhion,<note place="margin">The miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of oure nature.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knoweth nothynge of God, that is conceaued and borne in ſynne (as we all are), and of nature the chylde of wrath, and the enemye of God? How ſhuld we fynd the ryght waye and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therin, ſeynge that (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet Eſay ſayeth) we can do nothynge but go aſtray.
<pb facs="tcp:4561:10"/>Howe is it poſſible that we ſhulde defende our ſelues from the dyuell (which is a prince and lorde of this worlde, whoſe preſoners alſo we be euery one,) ſeynge that with all oure power and myghte, we can not do ſo muche as to hynder a ſmale leafe to hurte vs, or a poore flee from greuynge vs? Why wyll we poore wretched people boaſte ſo muche of great comforte, helpe, and counſell agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, agaynſt Gods wrath, and euerlaſtynge death, ſcyng that by our ſelues and other, we haue experience dayly and hourely, how we can nother counſell, nor comforte our ſelues in ſmal bodely neceſſityes?</p>
                     <p>Therfore conclude thus hardely:<note place="margin">I playne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon.</note> As lytle as a natural ſhepe can helpe it ſelfe in the thynges that be leeſt of all, but muſte loke for all benefites at his ſhepherdes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: much leſſe can a man rule, comforte, helpe or geue counſell vnto hymſelfe in thynges belongynge to ſaluacion, but muſte loke for all ſuch at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only hand of God his ſhepherd, with to fulfyl ony thyng for hys ſhepe that is to be done, is a thouſande tymes more wyllynge and diligent, then ony other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſhepherde in the worlde.</p>
                     <p>As for thys ſhepherde of whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete had ſpoken ſo longe before,<note place="margin">Chriſte is our ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde.</note> it is euen
<pb facs="tcp:4561:10"/>Chriſt oure louynge maſter, which is farre an other maner of ſhepherde then Moyſes, which is harde and extreme vnto his ſhepe, &amp;. dryueth them backe in to the wylderneſſe, where they fynde nother paſture, nor wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but playneſcarceneſſe, Exod .iii. But Chryſte is the gracyous and louynge ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde, which ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth after the famy ſhed and loſt ſhepe in the wylderneſſe, and ſeketh it there: And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he findeth it, he taketh it vp gladly vpon his ſhulders. Luc .xv. Yee &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his lyfe alſo for his ſhepe. Io .x. This muſt nedes be a louynge ſhepeherde. Who wolde not be glad then to be a ſhepe of his?</p>
                     <p>This ſhepherdes voyce wherwith he ſpeaketh and calleth vnto his ſhepe,<note place="margin">The ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes voyce.</note> is the holy goſpell, wherby we be taught that we optayne grace, remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng ſaluacion, not by Moſes law (wher thorow he putteth vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more feare, drede and diſpayre, whiche were to fearful, to ſore afrayed and diſpayred to muche afore,) but by Chryſt, whiche is the ſhepherde and byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of our ſoules .i. Pet. it whiche hath ſought vs myſerable and loſt ſhepe, and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vs out of the wyldernes, that is to ſay, from the lawe, from ſynne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, from the power of the deuell, from euerlaſtynge damnacion: And in that he gaue hys lyfe
<pb facs="tcp:4561:11"/>for vs, optayned he vs grace, remiſſion of ſynnes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, helpe and ſtrength agaynſt the deuell and all myſfortune, yee and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge lyfe alſo. This is now vnto the ſhepe of Chryſte, a louynge ſwete voyce, which they are hartely glad to heare, which they knowe ryghte well, and ordre them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues therafter. As for a ſtraunge voyce that ſoundeth otherwyſe, they nother knowe it, nor herken vnto it, but auoyde &amp; flye awaye from it. &amp;c. Ioh. x.</p>
                     <p>The paſture wherwith Chryſte fedeth his ſhepe,<note place="margin">The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</note> is alſo the comfortable goſpell, wherby the ſoules are fed and ſtrengthed, kepte from erroure, comforted in all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions and troubles, defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded agaynſte the craft and power of the deuell, and fynally delyuered out of all trouble. Neuertheleſſe for as muche as his ſhepe are not all alyke ſtronge, but ſome yet loſt, and ſcattred here and there abrode, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, ſycke, yonge and feble, he doth not therofre caſt them awaye but hathe much more reſpecte vnto them, &amp; careth more dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly for them, then for the other, that haue not ſuche nede. For as the prophete Ezechiel ſayeth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxxiiii. Chap. He ſeketh them that be loſt, bryngeth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them that be ſcattred abrode, byndeth vp ſuche as be wounded, loketh to them that
<pb facs="tcp:4561:11"/>be ſycke. And the weake lambes that be but yonge at the fyrſte (ſayeth Eſaye) he taketh vp into his armes, and beareth them, and ſuche as be with yonge ones, doth he dryue forth fayre and ſoftly. All this doth our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge mayſter Chriſt by the office of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge and diſtributynge of the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is ofte and with many wordes taught in other places. For to ſet it forth here worde by word as nede ſhulde requyre, it were to lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge. The prophete alſo hym ſelfe wyll declare it afterwarde in the Pſalme.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">We haue ben decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note>By this then maye we eaſely perceaue, how ſhamefully we haue ben ſeduced vnder the papacy. For Chryſt was not ſo louyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forthe vnto vs, as the dearly deloued prophetes, Apoſtles, and Chryſte hym ſelfe doth: but ſo fear fully was he deſcribed vnto vs, that we haue ben more afrayed of hym, then of Moyſes, yee we thought Moyſes doctryne muche more lyghter, and to haue much more ſwetneſſe in it, then the doctrine of Chryſt. And ſo we knewe nothynge els, but that Chryſt had ben a wrothfull iudge, whoſe diſpleaſure we myght haue reconcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with our good workes and with our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, &amp; whoſe pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we myght haue optay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the merytes and interceſſions of ſayntes. This is not onely a ſhamefull
<pb facs="tcp:4561:12"/>leſynge, and a miſerable deceauyng of poore conſciences, but alſo the hygheſt blaſphemy of the grace of god, a denyenge of the death, reſurreccion, and aſcenſion of Chryſte. &amp;c. and of all his vnoutſpeakeable benefytes, ſclaunderynge and condemnynge of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſpell, a deſtroyenge of faythe, and (in ſteade therof) a ſettynge vp of vtter abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynacions, lyes, and errours, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Yf this be not darkeneſſe, then can not I tell what darkeneſſe is.<note place="margin">Blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Yet coulde no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a maner perceaue it, but euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toke it for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> playne verite, &amp; yet vnto this day wyl our papyſtes nedes take it for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght way, and ſhed much innocent bloude for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Go to then, yf we can kepe and gide our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, yf we can preſerue our ſelues from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, yf we can optayne grace and remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes, reſyſt the deuell &amp; all miſfortune, ouercome ſynne and death by our owne me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytes: Then muſt all the ſcripture be falſe, which teſtifyeth of vs, how that of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues we are but loſt, ſcattred abrode, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, weake, and feble ſhepe. And ſo ſhulde we haue no nede of Chryſte to be ſhepherde, to ſeke vs, to brynge vs together, to gyde vs, to bynde vs vp, to loke vnto vs, &amp; to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vs agaynſte the deuell. And ſo hath he alſo geuen his lyfe for vs in vayne: For yf we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brynge
<pb facs="tcp:4561:12"/>al this to paſſe, &amp; optayne it through our owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and goodneſſe, then haue we no nede of Chryſtes helpe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">thys well.</note>But here thou heareſt the contrary: na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely that thou art but a loſt ſhepe, &amp; of thy ſelfe canſt not come to the ſhepherd agayn, but to go aſtraye onely that canſt thou well do. And yf Chryſt thy ſhepherd dyd not ſeke and fetch the agayne, thou muſt nedes be a praye vnto the wolfe. But nowe he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, ſeketh, fyndeth, and bryngeth the vnto his folde, that is to ſaye, into his Chryſten con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacion, through the worde &amp; ſacrament, geueth his lyfe for the, and holdeth the ſtyll by the ryght hande, leſt thou ſhuldeſt fall in to ony errour. There heareſt thou nothyng of thyne owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, of thyne owne good workes and merytes, except thou wylt call it ſtrength, a good worke and meryte to go aſtray, to be feble and loſt. Chryſt worketh, deſerueth, and ſheweth here his power one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It is he that ſeketh, beareth and gydeth the. He thorow his death deſerueth lyfe for the. He onely is ſtronge, and defendeth the leſt thou ſhuldeſt peryſſhe and be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye out of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Ioh. x. Vnto all this canſt thou do nothynge, ſaue applye thyne eares to heare, and with thankeſgeuynge to reccaue ſuche an vnoutſpeakeable treaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:13"/>and to learne to knowe well the voyce of thy ſhepherde, to followe hym, and to eſchue the voyce of ſtraungers.</p>
                     <p>Wherfore yf thou wylt be rychely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded for,<note place="margin">Take hede to thy ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herdes voyce.</note> both in body and ſoule, aboue all thynges take good hede than to the voyce of this ſhepherde, herken well what he ſayeth vnto the, let hym fede the, rule the, gyde the, defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the, comforte the. &amp;c. That is to ſaye, kepe the vnto his worde, be glad to heare it and to learne it, &amp; ſo no doute thou ſhalt be well prouyded for, both in body and ſoule.</p>
                     <p>By thys that hath ben ſpoken of hether to, I thynke it but eaſy to vnderſtand theſe wordes: <hi>The</hi> LORDE <hi>is my ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde.</hi> Yee and all the whole Pſalme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde. They are but few wordes: The LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE is my ſhepherde, but of a great weyght and pyth. The worlde maketh great boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge and crakynge of honoure, power, ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches, fauour, of men &amp;c. But the prophete maketh his boaſt of none of theſe: for they be all vncertayne and tranſytory. He ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth but few wordes and good: The LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE is my ſhepherde. Thus ſpeaketh a ſure and conſtant fayth, which turneth hyr back vpon euery thynge that is temporall &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitory, howe hye and precyous ſo euer it be, and turneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face and hart ſtrayght vnto
<pb facs="tcp:4561:13"/>the LORDE, whiche is onely and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and doth it hym ſelfe alone. Euen he, &amp; els none whether he be Kynge or Emperour (ſayeth he) is my ſhepherde. Therfore goeth he forwarde in all quyetneſſe and ſayeth. <hi>I ſhall lacke nothynge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> ſentence.</note>This doth he ſpeake in generall of all the benefytes bodely and gooſtly, that we receaue by the offyce of preachynge. As though he wolde ſaye: Yf the LORDE be my ſhepherde, then doutles I ſhall lacke nothynge. I ſhall haue abundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of meate drynke, clothynge, alyuynge, defence, peace, and all maner of neceſſaryes what ſo euer ſerueth for the ſuſtentacion of this lyfe.</p>
                     <p>For I haue a ryche ſhepherde, whiche ſhall not ſuffre me to lacke. Neuertheles he doth ſpeake mooſt ſpecyaſly of the ſpiritual goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and gyftes that the worde of God brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth with it, and ſayeth: For as much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE hath taken me amonge his flock, &amp; prouydeth for me with his owne paſture. that is: for as much as he hath rychely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me his holy worde, he ſhall not ſuffre me to haue ſcarceneſſe in ony thynge. He ſhal geue his bleſſynge vnto the worde, that it maye haue ſtrength, &amp; brynge forth frute in me. He ſhall lykewyſe geue me his ſprete to ſtande by me, &amp; to comforte me in al tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions
<pb facs="tcp:4561:14"/>and troubles, to make my harte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſure and certayne, and that I doute not therin, but that I am one of my ſhepherdes deare ſhepe. And he my faythfull ſhepherde, which wyll deale gently with me, as with a poore weake ſhepe, and wyll ſtrength my faythe, endue me alſo with other ſpirituall gyftes, comforte me in all troubles, heare me whan I call vpon hym, defende me from the wolfe, that is from the deuell, ſo that he ſhall not be able to do me harme. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally delyuer me from all myſfortune. This meaneth he whan he ſayeth: <hi>I ſhall lacke nothynge.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou wylt ſaye:<note place="margin">An obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </note> Yee but wherby ſhall I perceaue that the LORDE is my ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde? I can not perceaue that he dealeth ſo louyngly with me, as the Pſalme ſpeaketh, yee the contrary do I well perceaue. Dauid was an holy prophete, and a man dearly be loued vnto God, therfore coulde he eaſely talke of the matter, and beleue well as he ſayd. As for me, I ſhall not be able to do it after hym, for I am a poore ſynner.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">An anſwer</note>I haue declared aboue, that a ſhepe hath this good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; proper vertue in it, that it knoweth well the voyce of his ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde, and ordreth it ſelfe rather after the eares, then after the eyes. The ſame vertue
<pb facs="tcp:4561:14"/>doth Chryſte prayſe alſo in his ſhepe, whan he ſayeth Ioh. x. My ſhepe know my voyce. Now his voyce ſoundeth after this maner: I am a good ſhepherde, and geue my lyfe for my ſhepe. And I geue them euerlaſtyng lyfe, and they ſhall neuer peryſhe, &amp; no man ſhall plucke them out of my hande. Take good hede nowe vnto this voyce, and ordre thy ſelfe therafter. Yf thou ſo do, then be ſure that thou art one of Chryſtes ſhepe, &amp; he thy ſhepeherde, which knoweth the ryght well, and can cal the by name. Now yf thou haſt hym for thy ſhepeherde, then ſhalt thou verely lacke nothyng, yee thou haſt already that thou ſhuldeſt haue, euen euerlaſtynge lyfe. Item thou ſhalt neuer peryſſhe, nother ſhall ther be ony power ſo greate &amp; mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, as to be able to pluck y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out of his hand. Onely be thou ſure of this. For doutles this ſhepherdes voyce ſhall neuer fayle the. What wylt thou more?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Leaue not the voyce of thy ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herde.</note>But yf thou letteſt this voyce go, and ordreſt thy ſelfe after the ſyght of the eyes, and after the felynge of that olde Adam, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leſeſt thou the fayth and confidence, whiche thou as a ſhepe ſhuldeſt haue vnto hym as to thy ſhepeherde. And ſo falleth ther vpon the now one ymaginacion, now another, ſo that thou canſt not be in quyete, but diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:4561:15"/>by thy ſelfe and ſayeſt: Yf the LORDE be my ſhepherde, why ſuffreth he then the worlde to plage me and perſecute me ſo my ſerably, contrarye to all my deſeruynge? I ſyt amonge wolues, and am not ſure of my lyfe the twinkelynge of an eye, but I ſe no ſhepherde that wyll defende me. Item, why geueth he the deuell lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to do me ſo much harme, with feare and deſpayre? Beſydes this, I fynde my ſelfe all vnapte, feble, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacient, and laden yet with many ſynnes: I fynde no certaynte, but doutfulneſſe, no conſolacion, but fearfulneſſe and quakynge for the wrath of God. Whan begynneth he to declare in me, that he is my ſhepherde?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">what good followeth whan one rieueth faſt to gods worde.</note>Suche and many other mo wonderful cogitacions ſhalt thou haue, yf thou let his voyce and worde paſſe. But yf thou cleue ſtyll faſt vnto it, then ſuffreſt thou nother the deceatfulneſſe of the deuell, the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; madneſſe of the worlde, nother thyn owne infyrmite and vnworthyneſſe to ouer come the by temptacion: but goeſt on bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſayeſt: Whether the deuell, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, or myne owne conſcience do take parte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte me neuer ſo fearfly, yet wyll not I therfore take ouermuch thought. It muſte and ſhalbe thus, that who ſo euer is a ſhepe of the LORDE, he can not remayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted.
<pb facs="tcp:4561:15"/>Let it go with me as it maye, yee whether they ſeeth me, or roſt me, yet is this my comforte, that my ſhepherde hath geuen his lyfe for me. Beſydes this, he hath alſo a ſwete and louynge voyce, wherwith he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth and ſayeth: I ſhall neuer peryſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ther ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plucke me out of his hande, but I ſhall haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. This promyſe wyl he faythfully kepe with me, what ſo euer become vpon me. And thoughe ſomtyme ther chaunce a ſynne or other impediment by the reaſon of myne in fyrmite, yet wyll he not therfore caſt me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, for he is a louynge ſhepherde, whiche loketh to the weake ſhepe, byndeth vp theyr woundes, and healeth them. And to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that I ſhulde be the ſurer of this, &amp; not to doute theron, he hathe lefte me here the holy Sacrament for a token that it is ſo in dede.</p>
                     <p>Euen thus hath the prophete done. He was not mery alwaye, nother coulde he at al houres ſinge: <hi>The lord is my ſhepherd, I ſhall lack nothyng.</hi> He hath ben ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyme at many a great exige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yee al to many: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he nother felt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghteouſneſſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, nor helpe of god, but playne ſynne, the wrath of God, fearfulneſſe, diſpayre, the paynes of hell &amp;c. as he complayneth hymſelfe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:4561:16"/>Pſalmes. Neuertheleſſe he turneth hym from his owne felynge, and taketh holde of God by his promiſe concernynge Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that then was for to come, and caſteth this in his mynde: Howe ſo euer it ſtande with me, yet is thys the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of my hart, that I haue a gracyous &amp; mercyfull LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE, whiche is my ſhepeherde, whoſe worde and promyſe doth ſtrength and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me, therfore ſhall I lacke nothynge. And euen therfore hathe he wrytten thys and other Pſalmes, to the intent that we ſhulde be ſure, that in very temptacyons there is els where no counſel nor comforte to be found. And that this is the onely golden ſcience, namely, to cleue vnto the worde and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe of God, and to iudge after the ſame, and not aſter the felynge of the harte.</p>
                     <p>And ſo (no doute) ther ſhall followe helpe &amp; comforte, and not fayle in ony thynge.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <head>¶ Now followeth the ſeconde verſe.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He fedeth me in a grene paſture, and leadeth me to the freſh vvater.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the fyrſte verſe hathe the Prophete ſhortly comprehended the meanynge of the whol pſalme, namely that who ſo euer hath the LORDE for his ſhepherd, ſhall lack no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge. More than this doth not he teache
<pb facs="tcp:4561:16"/>in thys Pſalme, but onely ſetteth forth the ſame more at larg with goodly ornate wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and ſimilytudes how it chaunceth that they which are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſhepe, lack nothyng, and ſayeth: <hi>He fedeth me. &amp;c.</hi> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooſt thorow out the whole Pſalme (as his maner is oft tymes to do) he vſeth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, whiche ſignifye ſomwhat els than they ſounde. As whan he maketh mencion of the ſhepherde, of the fedyng, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grene paſture, of the freſh water, the ſtaf, the ſhepe hooke &amp;c. it is eaſy to perceaue that he wyll haue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what els vnderſtonde therby, then we men vſe to ſpeake therof. Suche maner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge is very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune in the ſcripture, and therfore ſhulde men take diligent hede ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, that they maye be accoſtumed wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and learne to vnderſtonde it.</p>
                     <p>But ſe howe well fauouredlye he can ſpeake. I am (ſayeth he) a ſhepe of the lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, whiche fedeth me in a grene paſture. &amp;c. A naturall ſhepe can not be better, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhepherde fedeth it in a pleaſaunt grene paſture, and beſyde freſſhe water. Yf it can haue thys, it thynketh no man vpon earth is more ryche or happyer then it. For there it fyndeth euery thynge that it can deſyre. A goodly thyck plentyfull graſſe, wherof it waxeth ſtronge and fat: A freſſhe water,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:17"/>wherewyth it can refreſſhe, and quycken it ſelfe. There hath it pleaſure and ioye: Euen ſo wyl Dauid ſaye herelyke wyſe, that God neuer ſhewed hym a greater grace and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefyte vpon earth, then thys, that he myght be in the place and among the people, where the worde and dwellynge of God, and the ryght Gods ſeruyce was. For where that treaſure is, there goeth it well both in the ſpirytuall and wordlye regiment. As yf he wolde ſaye: All the nacions and kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vpon earth are nothynge. They are (in dede) rycher, myghtyer, and more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then we Iewes, and make great boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge therof. They boaſt alſo of theyr wyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome and holyneſſe, for they haue goddes alſo whome they ſerue: yet wyth all theyr pompe and glory, they are but euen a playn wylderneſſe and deſert. For there is nother ſhepherde nor paſture, therfore muſte the ſhepe nedes ſtraye, be famyſhed &amp; peryſh: As for vs, though we haue many wylderneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes aboute vs, yet ſyt we here at reſt, ſafe, and mery in paradyſe, and in a pleaſaunt grene paſture, where there is plentye of graſſe and freſſhe water, and haue wyth vs oure ſhepherde, whiche fedeth vs, leadeth vs to the drynke, defendeth vs &amp;c. Thefore can we lacke nothynge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4561:17"/>
                        <note place="margin">The che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt good vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earthe is to haue gods word</note>Thys man had gooſtly eyes, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſawe he ryghtwell, what is the beſt and nobleſt good vpon earth. He maketh no boaſt of his kynglye worſhyppe and power, he knowlegeth wel that ſuch goodes are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the gyftes of God: nother runneth he fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; letteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lye: but vſeth them vnto the honoure of god, and geueth hym thankes therfore. But of this maketh he ſpeciallye hys boaſt, namelye, that the LORDE is hys ſhepherde, and he in hys paſture and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge: That is, that he hath Gods worde. This benefyte can he neuer forgette, but ſpeaketh therof maruaylous excellentlye, and with greate ioye, and prayſeth it farre aboue all the goodes vpon earth. And thys he doth in many Pſalmes, as in the .cxviii. where he ſayeth. The lawe of thy mouth is dearer vnto me then thouſandes of golde &amp; ſyluer. Item I loue thy commanndementes aboue golde and precious ſtone. O howe ſwete are thy wordes vnto my throte? Yee morethen hony vnto my mouthe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">What we ought here to learne.</note>Thys ſcience ſhulde we learne alſo, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melye, to let the worlde boaſt of theyr great ryches, honoure, power, &amp;c. For it is low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, vncertayne and tranſytory ware, whiche God caſteth into the dou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geon. It is a ſmall matter for hym to geue an vngracious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone
<pb facs="tcp:4561:18"/>(that blaſphemeth and dyſhonoureth hym agayne for hys rewarde) a kyngdome, a dukedome, or ony other worſhyppe, and good vpon earth. Theſe worldlye goodes are hys draff and ſwillynges, wherwyth he fylleth the hogges bellyes, that he is diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to kyll. But vnto hys chyldren (as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſpeaketh here therof) he geueth the ryght treaſure. Therfore ſhulde we as the deare chyldren and heyres of God, nother boaſte oure ſelues of oure wyſdome, ſtrength nor ryches: but of thys, that we haue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pearle: euen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worthy worde, where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by we knowe God oure louynge father and Ieſus Chriſt whome he hath ſent.<note place="margin">The word of God is oure trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> Thys is oure treaſure &amp; inheritaunce, whiche is ſure and euerlaſtynge, and better then al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good of the worlde. Who ſo hath thys, let hym ſuffre other men to gather mony together, to lyue voluptuouſly, to be proude, and hye mynded. But though he hymſelfe be deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and poore in the ſighte of the worlde, yet let not that tempte hym, but let hym thanke God for hys vnoutſpeakeable gyfte; &amp; pray that he maye abyde thereby. It maketh no matter how rych &amp; glorious we be here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth. Yf we kepe thys treaſure, we haue plentye of ryches &amp; honoure. Saynt Paule was a man of lytle reputacion, and poore
<pb facs="tcp:4561:18"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, hauynge the deuell &amp; the worlde very fearce agaynſt hym: But in the ſyghte of God he was a man ryght deare &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſet by. Beſydes this he was ſo poore, that he was fayne to get his liuyng wyth the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of hys handes. And yet for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate pouertye, he was rycher then the emperour of Rome: hauynge neuertheleſſe none other ryches, but the knowlege of Chriſte. For the which (ſayeth he Phil. <hi>3.</hi>) I counte all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (nothynge vpon earthe excepte,) very loſſe and dounge.</p>
                     <p>The God of mercye graunt vs grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we alſo after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enſample of Dauid, Paul &amp; other holy men, maye cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te oure treaſure (which is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had) as greate &amp; magnifie it aboue al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth. and hartelye to geue God thankes therfore that he hath weteſafed it vpon vs,<note place="margin">God hath done more for vs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for many other.</note> afore many thouſandes of other. He myght haue ſuffred vs to go aſtraye as well as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, Egypcians, Iewes, and other ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trers, which know not of that treaſure. Or els he myghte haue ſuffred vs ſtyll to be harde harted, as are the Papyſtes, that blaſpheme and condemne thys treaſure of oures. Where as he hath ſet vs now in hys owne grene medowe, and prouyded vs ſo rychely with good paſture and freſſhe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb facs="tcp:4561:19"/>It commeth euen of hys grace, therfore haue we the more to thanke hym for.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe.</note>As for the people of God or the holye congregacion of Chriſt, the prophet calleth it a grene medowe. For it is Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt garden, garnyſſhed and bewtyfyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all maner of ſpirituall gyftes.<note place="margin">The graſſe</note> The paſture or graſſe therin, is the worde of God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby the conſciences are ſtrengthed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſſhed. In the ſame grene medowe doth oure LORDE God gather hys ſhepe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether fedeth them therin with good graſſe, and refreſſheth them with freſſhe water. That is, he committeth vnto the holy Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten church the ſhepherdes office, deliuereth and geueth her the holy goſpel, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, to take charge and loke to hys ſhepe therewith, that they maye be rychely prouyded for, wyth doctrine, with comfort, wyth ſtrength,<note place="margin">what they be that fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſhepe in the wylder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> and with defence agaynſt al euell, &amp;c. As for thoſe that preach the lawe of Moſes or the commaundementes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they fede not the ſhepe in a grene paſture, but in the wylderneſſe (where they famyſh) and leade them to foule ſtynkynge waters, wherof they peryſh and dye.</p>
                     <p>By this allegorye of the grene paſture, wyll the the prophete declare the great abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daunce and ryches of the holy goſpell and
<pb facs="tcp:4561:19"/>of the knowlege of Chryſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full.<note place="margin">The great ryches of ſuche as beleue.</note> For lyke as the graſſe in a grene me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe ſtandeth goodly thycke and full, and euer groweth more and more: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo haue the faythfull not onely Gods worde wyth all ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſneſſe, but alſo the more they vſe it, and medle withall, the more it increaſeth and groweth amonge them. Therfore ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth he the wordes maruaylous playnly. He ſayeth not: he bryngeth me once or ofte into a grene paſture, but fedeth me ſtyl ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in, that I maye lye, take my reſt, and dwell euen in the myddes of the graſſe, and nede neuer to ſuffre hunger or ony ſcarceneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyde. For the worde that he here vſeth, maye be called lyenge or reſtynge, as a beaſt lyeth and reſteth vpon his foure fete. After the ſame maner doth Salomon ſpeake alſo in the .lxxi. Pſalme, where he prophecyeth of the kyngdome of Chryſte and the goſpell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhulde myghtely go thorowe and come in to all places, and ſayeth: Ther ſhall be an heape of corne in the earth hye vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. &amp;c. &amp; ſhalbe grene in the citye lyke graſſe vpon the earth. That Dauid alſo in thys Pſalme ſpeaketh lykewyſe of the goſpell, he declareth hymſelfe afterwarde, wher he ſayeth: <hi>He quyckeneth my ſoule.</hi> Ice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Thy ſtaffe &amp; thy ſhepehooke do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4561:20"/>
                        <note place="margin">The fyrſt frute of Gods worde.</note>This is now the fyrſt frute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, that the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſo inſtructe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by, that they increace in faith &amp; hope, learne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte all theyr doynges vnto God, &amp; what ſo euer they haue nede of, eyther in ſoule or body, to loke for it at his hande, &amp;c. <hi>And leadeth me to the freſſhe water.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d frute of Gods worde.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is the ſecond frute of gods worde It is vnto the faythfull not onely paſture and graſſe, wherby they are fylled &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in faythe. But it is alſo vnto them a goodly colde freſſhe water, where by they take refreſſhynge and comforte. Therfore leaueth he not there where he ſayde: He fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me in a grene paſture, but addeth this alſo vnto it: And leadeth me to the freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. As yf he wolde ſaye: In the greate heate whan the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne doth ſore burne. Pſal. c. xx. and I can haue no ſhadowe, then leadeth he me to the freſhe water, geueth me drynke, and refreſſheth me, that is: in all maner of troubles, anguiſhes, and neceſſities, gooſtly and bodely, whan I knowe not els where to fynde helpe or comforte, I holde me vnto the worde of grace. There onely and no where els do I fynde the ryght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacion &amp; refreſhynge, &amp; that plenteouſly. Now wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as he ſpeaketh here of this comforte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed wordes, he talketh of it in another
<pb facs="tcp:4561:20"/>place with playne and manyfeſt wordes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.</note> &amp; ſayeth: Yf thy worde were not my comfort and delyte, I ſhulde peryſſhe in my trouble. I wyll neuer forget thy worde, for in my trouble it is my conſolacion, yet thy worde quyckeneth me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Why the ſcripture rehearſeth ſo oft this ſimilitude.</note>Neuertheleſſe continueth ſtyll in the ſimilitude of the ſhepherde and of the ſhepe. And (no doute) it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun in al the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. For of the ſhepe and other cattell had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes theyr beſt lyuynge, and were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſhepeherdes, as was Dauid and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes. Therfore is this ſimilitude ofty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſpoken of in the ſcripture. But Dauid ſpeaketh of this matter after the nature of the contry. For the lande of promyſe is an whote drye, ſandye, &amp; ſtony la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, which hath many wylderneſſes &amp; lytle water. Therfore in the fyrſt boke of Moſes it was more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once declared, how that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heythen ſhepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſtroue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſhepeherdes of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes becauſe of water. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche cauſe in the ſame contry they toke it for a ſpeciall treaſur, yf they myght haue water for theyr cattell (In our contryes we knowe not ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, for ther is water ynoughe euery where.) Of this dyd Dauid ſe, and he rehearſeth it for a ſpeciall benefyte, to be vnder the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodye of the LORDE, whyche ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:4561:21"/>not onely fede hym in a grene paſture, but alſo in the heate, bryngynge hym to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> freſh water, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Shortly, his meanynge is to declare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as lytle as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can come to the knowlege of God and the truthe &amp; to the ryght fayth without the worde of God: So lytle can ther ony comforte and peace of conſcience be founde without the ſame.<note place="margin">Without gods word ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s conſcience be at reſt.</note> The worldly haue alſo theyr comforte and ioye, howe be it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> endureth but the twinkelynge of an eye. Whan trouble and anguyſh commeth (and ſpecyally the laſt houre) it goeth awaye. As Salomon ſayeth:<note place="margin">Pro. <hi>14.</hi>
                        </note> After laughter, commeth ſorowe: and after ioye, commeth heuyneſſe. But as for them that drynke of this freſſhe and lyuynge water, they maye well ſuffre trouble &amp; diſeaſe in the worlde, but they ſhal neuer lacke the true conſolacion. And ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally whan it commeth to the poynt, the leafe turneth ouer with them, whiche is as much to ſaye, as: After ſhorte wepynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euerlaſtynge laughter: and after a lytle ſorow, commeth excellent ioye. ii. Cor. iiii. For they ſhall not wepe &amp; mourne both here and there, but as Chryſte ſayeth: Bleſſed are you that wepe here, for ye ſhall laugh. Luce. vi.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He quyckeneth my ſoule and bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb facs="tcp:4561:21"/>me forthe in the vvaye of rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe for his names ſake.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Spiritual paſture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> water.</note>Here doth the prophet declare hymſelfe of what maner of paſture and freſh water he ſpake: namely, euen of the ſame y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth and quyckeneth the ſoule. This can be nothynge els but Gods worde. But for as muche as our LORDE God hath two maner of wordes, the lawe, and the goſpell, the prophete whan he ſayeth: <hi>He quycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth my ſoule</hi> geueth ſuffycienlty to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde that he ſpeaketh not here of the lawe, but of the goſpell.<note place="margin">The lawe</note> The lawe can not quycken the ſoule, for it is a worde that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth and commaundeth vs to loue God wyth all our hartes, &amp;c. and our neyghbour as our ſelues. Who ſo doth not this, hym it condempneth, and ſpeaketh this ſentence ouer hym: Curſed be euery man which doth not all that is written in the boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law. Deut. <hi>27.</hi> Galat. <hi>3.</hi> Now is it certayne that no man vpon earth doth this: therfore com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth the lawe with his iudgement, fearyng and vexynge the conſciences. And yf ther be no helpe, it goeth thorow, ſo that they muſt nedes fall into diſpayre, and be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned for euer. Of this occaſion doth S. Paule ſaye:<note place="margin">Rmo. <hi>3.</hi>
                        </note> By the lawe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth but the knowlege of ſynne. Item, the lawe cauſeth but wrath.<note place="margin">Rmo. <hi>4.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4561:22"/>
As for the goſpell, it is a bleſſed worde. It requyreth none ſuche of vs,<note place="margin">The goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</note> but bryngeth vs tydynges of all good, namely, that God hath geuen vs poore ſynners his onely ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to be our ſhepherde, to ſeke agayne vs fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and diſperſed ſhepe, and to geue his lyfe for vs, that he myght ſo delyuer vs from ſynne, from euerlaſtynge death, and from the power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuel. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grene graſſe and the freſh water, where w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the LORDE quyckeneth oure ſoules. And thus are we made lowſe from euell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences and heuy thoughtes. Of this ſhal we ſpeake more in the .iiii. verſe. <hi>He bryngeth me forth in the waye of ryghteouſneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here (ſayeth he) doth not the LORDE my faythfull ſhepherde leaue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he fedeth me in a grene medowe, &amp; leadeth me to the freſh water, &amp; ſo quickeneth my ſoule, but he bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth me forth alſo in the right waye, that I departe not aſyde, go aſtraye, &amp; ſo peryſſhe. That is, he holdeth me faſt to the pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that I be not deceaued by falſe ſpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">To be led in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght way what it is.</note> and that I fall not awaye by ony other temptacion or offence. Item, that I maye know, how I ought to leade myn outward conuerſacion &amp; lyfe, &amp; that I ſuffre not my ſelfe to be perſwaded by the holynes and ſtrayte lyfe of ypocrites. Item, what is the
<pb facs="tcp:4561:22"/>true doctrine, fayth and ſeruice of God, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">An excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertue of Gods worde.</note>This is now agayne a goodly frute &amp; vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, that they whiche cleue faſt there vnto, do not onely receaue ſtrength &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule therby, but are preſerued alſo from vntrue doctrine &amp; falſe holyneſſe. Many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> optayne this treaſure, but they can not kepe it. For as ſoone as a man is to bolde &amp; preſumptuous, and thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hymſelfe ſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, it is done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym. Or euer he can loke aboute hym, he is deceaued. For the deuell alſo can pretende holyneſſe, and tranſforme hymſelfe into an angell of lyght, as ſaynt Paul ſayeth: And euen ſo lykewyſe can his minyſters ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, as though they were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers of ryghteouſneſſe, &amp; come i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhepes clothyng amonge the flocke of Chryſt, but inwardly are they rauenynge wolues. Therfore is it good here to watch &amp; praye (as the prophete doth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt verſe) that our ſhepherd maye kepe vs by this treaſure whiche he hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do not this, certaynly they ſhall leſe it. And the ende of that man (as Chriſt ſayeth) ſhall be worſe then the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge.<note place="margin">Luce. <hi>11.</hi>
                        </note> For they ſhall afterwarde become y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt poyſened enemyes of Chriſtes flock, and do more harme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr falſe doctryne, then the tyrauntes with the ſwearde. This
<pb facs="tcp:4561:23"/>had ſaynt Paul well proued by the falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that made the Corinthians &amp; Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians to erre ſo ſoone, and afterwarde made diuiſion in all Aſia. We ſe it our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues alſo this daye by the Anabaptiſtes and other falſe ſpretes. <hi>For his names ſake.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The name of God.</note>The name of God is the preachyng of God, wherby he is magnifyed and knowen to be gracyous, mercyfull, longe ſufferyng, true, faythfull, &amp;c. which (notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge that we be the chyldren of wrath, and gyltye of euerlaſtynge death) forgeueth vs all our ſynnes, and taketh vs for his owne chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and inheritours. This is his name, thys doth he cauſe to be proclamed by his worde. Thus wyll he be knowen, magnifyed, and honoured. And (accordynge vnto the fyrſte commaundement) he wyl euen thus declare hymſelfe towarde vs, as he hath cauſed it to be preached of hym. Lyke as he doth ſtyll, ſtrengtheth and quyckeneth our ſoules ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, and kepeth vs that we fall not in to erroure, hetteth vs lyuynge for our body, and preſerueth vs from all miſfortune.</p>
                     <p>This honoure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſo is as we haue now ſayd, is geuen hym onely of them that cleue faſt vnto his worde, theſe beleue &amp; confeſſe playnly, that all the gyftes &amp; goodes whiche they haue gooſtly and bodely, they receaue
<pb facs="tcp:4561:23"/>them of God, euen of his mere grace &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe. That is to ſaye: <hi>For his names ſake,</hi> not for theyr owne workes and deſeruyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For this do they geue thankes vnto hym, and declare the ſame vnto other. This honour can not be geuen vnto God, of ony preſumptuous iuſticiaryes, as heretikes &amp; falſe ſpretes, or enemyes and blaſphemers of Gods worde, for they magnifye not his name, but theyr owne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And though I walke in the valley of the ſhadowe of death, yet fear I no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for thou art with me. Thy ſtaffe and thy ſhephooke do comforte me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hetherto hath the prophete declared, that they whiche haue &amp; loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacke nothynge. For the LORDE is theyr ſhepherde, which doth not only fede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a grene paſture, &amp; leadeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the freſhe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be fat, ſtronge, and refreſhed both bodely &amp; gooſtly: but alſo taketh ſuche care for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be not weery of the good paſture &amp; freſh water, leauyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grene me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe, &amp; departe agayne from the ryght way into the wylderneſſe. This is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt parte of this Pſalme. Nowe teacheth he farther how that they whiche are the ſhepe of thys ſhepeherde,<note place="margin">What the prophet teacheth in this verſe</note> be compaſſed aboute with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ieopardyes and miſfortunes. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4561:24"/>that LORDE (ſayeth he) not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but delyuered them alſo out of al te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptacions &amp; troubles. For he is amonge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nowe after what maner he is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, he declareth lykewyſe well fauouredly.</p>
                     <p>Here thou ſeyft y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God goeth forth, and as ſoone as ther be ony y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> receaue it, &amp; abide by it, immediatly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuell &amp; all his angels ſteppe forth &amp; moue the worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power therof agaynſt it, to put it downe, &amp; vtterly to deſtroye them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue it &amp; knowlege it.<note place="margin">Perſecuci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note> For loke what our LORD god ſpeaketh or doth, it muſt be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; go thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre. This is very nedfull for chryſten men to knowe, els myght they fayle &amp; thynke thus in theyr myndes: How ſtondeth this together: The prophet ſayeth afore: The LORDE is my ſhepherd, I ſhall lacke nothynge. And here he ſayeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, namely, that he muſte walke in the darke valley. And in the nexte verſe followynge he confeſſeth that he hath enemyes? Where by he geueth ſufficiently to vnderſtand that he lacketh many, yee all thynges. For he that hath enemyes and lyeth in a darke val<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ley, ſeyth no lyghte, that is to ſaye, he hath nother comforte nor hope, but is forſaken of euery man, and euery thynge is blacke &amp; darke before his eyes, yee eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fayre clear
<pb facs="tcp:4561:24"/>So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. How is this true then that he ſhulde lacke nothynge?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">We maye not ordre our ſelues after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our warde ſyght.</note>Here muſt thou not ordre thy ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thyne owne eyes, &amp; followe natural rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, as doth the worlde, vnto whome it is vnpoſſyble to ſe this ryche and gloryous comforte of Chryſten men, that they ſhulde lacke nothynge. Yee certaynly they holde that the contrary is true, namely, that ther are no people vpon earth more poore, more myſerable, and more vnhappy then chriſten men: Yee with all theyr diligence &amp; corage helpe they therto, that they maye be mooſt abhominably perſecuted, ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyſhed, ſhamed, and put to death. And in ſo doynge, they thynke they do God ſeruyce therin. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth therfore outwardly as though chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men were but ſhepe dryuen awaye and forſaken of God, and geuen ouer already in to the wolues mouthes, and to be euen ſuch, as lacke nothynge but altogether.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon.</note>Agayne, they that ſerue that greate God Mammon or the belly, appeare in the worlde, to be thoſe good ſhepe whiche (as the Pſalme ſayeth) lacke nothynge: beynge rychely prouyded for of God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted and preſerued from all parell and myſfortune. For they haue theyr owne hartes deſyre, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure, good, ioye, pleaſure, euery mans fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:25"/>&amp;c. Nother nede they be afrayed to be perſecuted or put to death for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faythes ſake. For as longe as they put not theyr truſt in Chryſt the onely true ſhepherd, nor knowlege hym, whether they beleue on the deuell or his da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, or do what ſo euer they wyll beſyde with couetouſneſſe. &amp;c. they are taken not onely for well doers therin, but alſo for the lyuyng ſayntes, which byde ſtyll by the olde fayth, and wyll not be deceaued thorowe hereſye, whiche is (as Dauid tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth here) that the LORDE onely is the ſhepeherde. So abhominable and greueous mortall ſynne is it to beleue on this ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde and to knowlege hym,<note place="margin">The pope wyll not forgeue hym, that putteth his whole truſt in Chriſt.</note> that ther cam neuer ſuche a ſynne vpon earth. For euen the Popes holynes which els can diſpenſe with all ſynnes and forgeue them, can not remytte this onely cryme.</p>
                     <p>Therfore (I ſaye) in this thynge do not thou followe the worlde &amp; thyne owne reaſon, whiche whyle they iudge after the outwarde appearaunce, become foolyſſhe, &amp; holde the prophete but for a lyar in that he ſayeth: <hi>I ſhall lacke nothynge.</hi> But (as I ſayde afore) holde thou the faſte vnto the worde and promyſes of God, herken vnto thy ſhepherde, how and what he ſayeth vnto the, and ordre thy ſelfe accordynge vnto hys
<pb facs="tcp:4561:25"/>voyce, not accordynge to that which the eye ſeyth or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte feleth. And ſo haſte thou the victory. Thus doth the prophere: He confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that he walketh in the valley of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of death.<note place="margin">Howe the Prophet behaueth hymſelf in tentacion &amp; trouble.</note> That is, that he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed aboute with trouble, heuyneſſe, anguyſſhe, neceſſite, &amp;c. as thou mayſt ſe more at large in hys ſtoryes, and other Pſalmes. Item, that he hath nede of comforte, wherby it is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly declared that he is in heuyneſſe. Item, that he hathe enemyes. And yet he ſayeth: Though my tentacions were mo and greate, and though I were in a worſe caſe: Yee though I were in deathes mouth alreadye, yet do not I feare onye myſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Not that I am able to helpe my ſelfe thorowe myne owne prouyſion, trauayle, laboure or ſuccurre. Nother do I truſt to myne owne wyſdome, vertue, kynglye po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and ryches: For in thys matter, the helpe, counſel, comforte, and power of all men is farre to lytle.</p>
                     <p>But thys is it that doth it, euen that the LORDE is wyth me. As yf he wolde ſay: Certaynly of myne owne behalfe I am feble, in heuyneſſe, vexed, and compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute wyth al maner of parell and miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. My harte alſo and conſcience is not quyete, becauſe of my ſynnes. I fele an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb facs="tcp:4561:26"/>fearfulneſſe of death, and hel, ſo that I myght in a maner diſpayre. But though al the worlde, yee and the gates of hell be ſet agaynſt me, yet wyll I therfore not be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coraged. Yee I wyll not be afrayed for all the myſfortune and payne that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſaye vpon me. For the LORDE is wyth me. The LORDE (I ſaye) whiche made heauen and earthe and all that therin is, vnto whom al creatures, angels, deuels, men, ſynne, death, &amp;c. are ſubiecte. Summa, he that hath all thynges in hys owne power is my counſelgeuer, my comforter, my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, and helper. Therfore am I afrayed of no myſfortune.</p>
                     <p>After thys maner doth Aſaph ſpeake al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo in the .lxxii.<note place="margin">Iſaph</note> Pſalme, where he comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Chriſten agaynſt that greate ſtomblynge block, that the vngodlye haue ſuch proſperyte vpon earth: And that the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſayntes of God on the other ſyde are euer plaged, &amp;c. and ſayeth: Yf I haue but the o LORDE, I paſſe not vpon heauen nor earth. Though both body and ſoule ſhulde peryſſhe. Yet thou o God, arte the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of my harte and my porcion. Now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what maner the LORDE is with hym, he ſheweth farther more, and ſayeth,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thy ſtaf and thy ſhepehooke do com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte
<pb facs="tcp:4561:26"/>me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Howe the LORD is <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many faithful men,</note>The LORDE (ſayth he) is wyth me, but not bodely, that I may ſe or heare hym. Thys preſence of the LORDE wherof I ſpeake, is not comprehended wyth the fyue wyttes. Onely fayth ſeyth it. The ſame is ſure, that the LORDE is nyer vnto vs, then we are to oureſelues. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? euen by the worde. Therfore ſayeth he: <hi>Thy ſtaf and thy ſhepehooke comforte me:</hi> As yf he wolde ſaye: In al my troubles and neceſſityes I fynde nothynge vpon earth, whereby I maye be helped to be at reſt. Onely the worde of God is my ſtaf &amp; ſhepehooke where by I holde me, and ſtonde vp agayne. And ſure I am lykewyſe by it, that the LORDE is with me, and doth not onely ſtrengthe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me by the ſame worde in all troubles and tentacions: but alſo delyuereth me from all myne enemyes, ſpyte of the deuell, and the worlde. Wyth theſe wordes: <hi>Thy ſtaf and thy ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooke do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth he agayne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepherde &amp; the ſhepe,<note place="margin">The ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepherd</note> &amp; wyll ſay thus much: Lyke as a bodely ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herde ruleth his ſhepe with the ſtaf or ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooke, &amp; leadeth them to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſture &amp; to freſh water, where they fynd meate and drynke, and defendeth them wyth the ſhepehooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:4561:27"/>all parell: Euen ſo doth the LORD the true ſhepeherde, gyde and rule me with hys ſtaf. That is to ſaye, with hys worde: to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that in hys ſyght I ſhuld walke wyth a good belefe and a mery conſcience, and knowe to beware of vntrue doctryne and falſe holyneſſe. Beſyde thys, he defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me alſo agaynſt al ieopardy and myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, bodely and goofily, and deliuereth me from all myne enemyes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſtaf, that is to ſaye, wyth the ſame worde doth he ſtrengthe and comforte me ſo rychelye, that ther is no myſfortune ſo greate, whether it be bodelye or goofilye, but I am able to come out of it, and to ouercome it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">this goeth ſpiritually to worke.</note>By thys thou ſeyſte that the prophete ſpeaketh here of no helpe, defence, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of man. Nother draweth he out ony ſwearde. &amp;c. It goeth here all ſecretely and preuelye to worke, euen by the worde. So that no man can ſpye thys defence &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, but onely they that beleue. And here doth Dauid wryte a generall rule for all Chriſten men, whiche is well to be noted: Namelye, that ther is none other meane waye vpon earth for onye man to be dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of all tentations, ſaue onely to caſt all hys burthen vpon God, and to hold hym faſte by hys worde of grace, to cleue
<pb facs="tcp:4561:27"/>ſurelye vnto it, and in no wyſe to ſuffre it to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym. Who ſo doth thys, can be content, whether he be in proſperite or aduerſyte, whether he lyue or dye. And fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally he can endure, and muſt nedes proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per agaynſt all deuels, the worlde, and myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. Thys me thynke is a greate prayſe of the good worde of God, and a greater power is aſcrybed here vnto it, then is the power of all angels &amp; men. Thus doth S. Paule prayſe it alſo Rom. i. The Goſpell (ſayeth he) is the power of God, for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of all them that beleue thereon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The office of preahige</note>And with thys doth the prophet touche the offyce of preachynge, for by the mouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preachynge of the worde whiche goeth in at the eares, and that the harte taketh holde vpon thy fayth, and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſacramentes doth oure LORDE God brynge aſſ thys to paſſe in his Chriſten congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, to the intent that the people maye haue fayth, be ſtrenthed in belefe, and preſerued in the true doctryne. Item, that they maye fynally endure agaynſt all temptacions of the deuell and the worlde. For ſence the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of the worlde hathe God dealte thus with all his ſayntes by his worde, and beſyde the ſame hath he geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outwarde tokens of grace. This I ſaye becauſe that no man ſhuld take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym without theſe
<pb facs="tcp:4561:28"/>meanes to medle with God, or to choſe hym ſelfe a peculyar waye vnto heauen, els ſhall he fall and breake his necke, as the pope and his hath done. And as the Anabaptiſtes &amp; other ſedicious ſpretes do yet this daye.</p>
                     <p>And with theſe wordes: <hi>Thy ſtaffe and thy ſhepehooke do comfort me</hi> wyll the prophete ſhewe ſome ſpeciall thynge. As yf he wolde ſay: Moſes is aſhepherde lykwyſe, and hath alſo a ſtaffe &amp; a ſhephooke: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he doth nothynge els but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell and punyſſhe his ſhepe, and ouerladeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with an intollerable burthen, Act. xv. Eſay. ix. Therfore is he a fearfull &amp; a terrible ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhepe are afrayed, and flye from hym. Neuertheſeſſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> LORDE with thy ſtaffe and ſhephooke, compelleſt not thy ſhepe, nother makeſt them afrayd, nor ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeſt them, but geueſt them comforte.</p>
                     <p>Therfore ſpeaketh he here of the office of preachynge the newe Teſtament, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby tydynge is brought vnto the worlde, that Chriſt came vpon earthe to ſaue ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: and therby hath optayned them ſuche a ſaluacion, that he hath geuen hys lyfe for them. All they that beleue thys ſhall not peryſhe: but haue euerlaſtynge lyfe. Ioh. iii. Thys is the ſtaf and ſhephooke, wherby the ſoules take refreſhynge,<note place="margin">The ſtaf &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhephoke.</note> comforte, and ioye.
<pb facs="tcp:4561:28"/>Wherfore in the ſpirytuall ſhepefolde, that is to ſaye, in the kyngdome of Chriſte, ther ought none other ſawe to be preached, but the Goſpell, which the prophet with ornate wordes calleth the ſtaf and ſhephooke of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, whereby they be ſtrengthed in fayth, refreſſhed in theyr hartes, and receaue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacion in all maner of troubles, and euen at the poynt of death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">what they be thatlede Chriſtes ſhepe in a grene me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe</note>They that ſo preach, vſe the ſpirytuall ſhepherdes offyce aryght, fede the ſhepe of Chriſt in a grene medowe, leade them to the freſh water, refreſh theyr ſoules, kepe them that they be not deceaued, &amp; comforte them with the ſtaf and ſhephooke of Chriſt, &amp;c. And where thou heareſt ſuche one, be ſure thou heareſt Chriſt hymſelfe. Suche men alſo oughte to be taken for true ſhepherdes: that is to ſaye, for the mynyſters of Chriſt, and the ſtewardes of God. Nother oughte it to be regarded, that the worlde cryeth out vpon them, and calleth them heretikes and deceauers. Agayne, they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teach ony thynge els contrarye to the Goſpell, cauſynge men to truſt to theyr owne workes, merites, &amp; to theyr owne fayned holineſſe, theſe no doute, though they boaſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer ſo muche to be the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles, &amp; decke them ſelues with the name and tytle of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten
<pb facs="tcp:4561:29"/>ſtenchurch, yeethough they rayſed vp dead men, yet are they wolues and murtherers: whiche ſpare not the flocke of Chriſt, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them abrode, torment them, and kyll the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not onely ſpiritually, but bodely alſo, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mayeſe now before theyr eyes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that the worde of God hath in this Pſalme.</note> Lyke as the prophete here afore doth call Gods worde or the goſpell, graſſe, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the ryght waye, a ſtaffe, &amp; a ſhephooke: Euen ſo afterwarde in the fyfth verſe he calleth it, a table prepared, an oyntment, &amp; a full cuppe. And thys ſimſlitude of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and cuppe doth he take out of the olde teſtament from the Gods ſeruyce of the Iewes, and ſayeth euen in a maner the ſame that he had ſayd afore, namely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they whiche haue the worde of God, are ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chely prouyded for in all poyntes, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge the ſoule, and body, ſaue onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſpeaketh it here wyth other fygures and allegoryes. Fyrſt bryngeth he in the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the table,<note place="margin">A table.</note> where vpon the ſhewe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breads laye contynually. Exod. xxv. xl. And then declareth he what the ſame dyd ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth, and ſayeth:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou prepareſt a table before me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt myne enemyes, thou anoynteſt myne heade wyth oyle, and fylleſt my cuppe full.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4561:29"/>
Here doth he knowlege playnly, that he hath enemyes. But he ſayeth he kepeth hym from them, and dryueth them backe, by this meanes, namely, becauſe the LORDE hath prepared a table before hym agaynſt thoſe his enemyes. Is not this a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full defender? I wolde haue thought he ſhulde haue prepared before hym a ſtronge wall, a myghtye hulworke, depe dyches, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and other harneſſe &amp; weapens, where by he myght be ſure from his enemyes, and diſcomfite them. And now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth he and prepareth before hym a table, to eate and drynke on, and ſo to ſmyte hys enemyes.</p>
                     <p>There coulde I be content to fyght alſo, yf the enemyes myghte be ouercome without ony teopardye, care, trauayle and laboure. And I to do nothyngeels but to ſyt at a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to eate and drynke and be mery.</p>
                     <p>With theſe wordes: <hi>Thou prepareſt a table befor me agaynſt myne enemyes,</hi> wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet declare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">The great power of Gods worde.</note> &amp; wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful power of the worde of God. As yf he wolde ſay: Thou offreſt me ſuch kyndneſſe (OLORDE) and fedeſt me ſo well and rychely at thy table, whiche thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for me, that is: Thou endueſt me ſo pſenteouſly with the exceadynge knowlege of thy good worde, ſo that thorow the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:4561:30"/>I haue not onely plenteous conſolacion in wardly in my harte: agaynſt myne owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell conſcience, agaynſt feare and drede of death, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Godt but outwardly alſo thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame worde I am become ſo valeaunt and ſo inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a giaunt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al myne enemyes can bryng nothynge to paſſe agaynſt me. The more wroth, madde, and vnreaſonable they are agaynſt me, the leſſe I regarde it. Yet I am ſo much the more quyete in my ſelfe, glad &amp; content. And that of none other occaſion, ſaue onely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue thy worde. The ſame geueth me ſuch power and corage agaynſt all myne enemyes: So that whan they rage fearſly and are mooſt madde of all, I am better content in my mynde, then yf I ſatte at a table where I myght haue all that my harte coulde deſyre, meate, drynke, myrthe, pleaſure, mynſtrelſye, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">An hye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods worde.</note>There heareſt thou agayne, how hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this holy Dauid magnifyeth &amp; prayſeth the good worde of God, namely: how that by the ſame, they that beleue, ouercome and wynne the victory, agaynſt the deuell, the worlde, the fleſhe, ſynne, a mans owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and agaynſt death. For yf a man haue the worde, and take ſure holde of it by fayth, then muſt all theſe enemyes (whiche
<pb facs="tcp:4561:30"/>els are inuincible) be fayne to geue backe, and to yelde them ſelues. And it is a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaylous victory and power, yee and a very ſtoute boaſtynge of ſuche as beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſubdue and ouercome all theſe horrible (yee and in maner almyghtye) enemyes, not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ragynge, not wyth bytynge, not wyth reſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge, not with ſtrykyng agayne, not with takynge of vengeaunce, not wyth ſekynge of counſell and helpe here and there: but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eatynge, drynkynge, pleaſure, ſyttynge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge mery and takyng of reſt. Which thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges (as it is ſayde afore) come all to paſſe thorowe the worde.<note place="margin">To eate and dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke what it is</note> For to eate and drynke is called in the ſcripture, to beleue, to take ſure holde on Gods worde, wherout ther followeth, peace, ioye, comforte, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall reaſon of man.</note> Natural reaſon can geue no iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in this wonderfull victory of the faythfull, for here commeth the matter to paſſe cleane contrarye to the outwarde ſenſes of man. The worlde doth alwaye perſecute &amp; ſlaye the Chriſten, as the mooſt hurtfull people vpon earthe. Now whan naturall reaſon ſeyth thys, it can not thynke otherwyſe but that the Chriſten lye vnder: &amp; agayne, that theyr enemyes preuayle and haue the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Thus dyd the Iewes intreate Chriſte, the Apoſtles, and the faythfull, and put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb facs="tcp:4561:31"/>euer to execucion. Whan they had ſlayne them, or at the leeſt baniſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then cryed they: Now haue we y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory: theſe fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that haue hurte vs, ſhall now trouble vs no more: Now ſhall we handle euery thyng as we wyll. But whan they thought them ſelues to haue bene ſureſt of all, our LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE God ſent vpon them the Romaynes, whiche dealte ſo horriblye wyth them, that it is a terrible thynge to heare. Then after certayne hundreth yeares, as for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes (whiche thorow oute all the empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of Rome had ſlayne manye thouſande martyrs) God rewarded them afterward, and ſuffred the cytie of Rome in few yeares to be four tymes ſpoyled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gothies and Vandalyes, &amp; finally to be brent, deſtroyed, and the empyre to decaye. Who had now y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory? The Iewes and Romaynes that ſhed the bloud of ſayntes, lyke water? or the poore Chriſten, that ſuffred them ſelues to be ordred lyke ſlaughter ſhepe, and had none other harneſſe and weapen, but the good worde of God?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Howe it goeth with the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue in Chriſte.</note>Thus doth Dauid declare wyth theſe wordes, howe it goeth wyth the holy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (For he ſpeaketh not here of his owne perſon only) ſetteth her forth in hyr coloures, and deſcrybeth her well fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouredly,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:31"/>Namely: how that in the ſyghts of God, ſhe is euen as a pleaſaunt grene medowe, whiche hath plentye of graſſe and freſſhe water. That is to ſay, that ſhe is the paradyſe and pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t garden of God, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhhed wyth all hys gyftes, and hath hys vnoutſpeakeable treaſure, the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and that good worde, wherewyth he inſtructeth, gydeth, refreſheth, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his flocke. But in the ſyght of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde hath thys congregacion a farre other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearaunce, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as though ſhe were a blacke darke valleye, where a man can ſe nother pleaſure, nor ioye: but trouble, ſorowe, and aduerſyte. For the deuell wyth al his power ſetteth hym ſelfe agaynſt it, for thys trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſake. Inwardly plageth he the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion of God wyth hys venymous fyrye dartes: Outwardly treadeth he her downe by ſectes and offences. Then kyndleth he alſo hys brande vpon her, euen the worlde, which mynyſtreth vnto her all ſorowe and heuyneſſe of harte, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perſecutynge, ſklaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drynge, blaſphemynge, condemnynge, and murthurynge: In ſo muche that it were no wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der that deare flock of Chriſt were vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed in the twyncklynge of an eye, by ſuch greate ſoltytye and myght, both of the deuell, and of the worlde. For ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not
<pb facs="tcp:4561:32"/>kepe her ſelfe from hyr enemyes, they are farre to ſtronge, to deceatfull and to mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye for her. She is euen as the prophet doth here deſcrybe her: An innocent, ſymple, and wapenleſſe lambe, whiche nother wyll nor can do ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harme, but is alway readye not onely to do good, but alſo to take euell for good. Howe happeneth it then that the congregacion of Chriſt in ſuch weakneſſe,<note place="margin">Howe the flocke of Chriſt win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth.</note> can eſcape the craftineſſe and tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny of the deuell and the worlde? The LORDE is hyr ſhepeherde, therfore lacketh ſhe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge. He fedeth and refreſſheth her, gooſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and bodely, he kepeth her in the ryght waye, he geueth her alſo hys ſtaf and ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooke in ſteade of a ſwearde, which ſhe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not in the hand, but in the mouth. And not onely comforteth the ſorowfull ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth, but dryueth awaye the deuell alſo and all hys Apoſtels, be they neuer ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll and ſpitefull. Beſydes thys, the LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE hath prepared for her alſo a table, and Eaſter lambe. Whan hyr enemyes are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye wrothfull, gnaſſhe theyr tethe together ouer her, are mad, vnreaſonable, in a rage, and out of theyr wyttes, and take all theyr ſotyltye, power, and myghte to helpe them, for to deſtroye her vtterlye: Then doth the beloued bryde of Chriſte ſet her downe at
<pb facs="tcp:4561:32"/>hyr LORDES table, eateth the Eaſter-lambe, drinketh of the freſh water, is mery, and ſyngeth: <hi>The</hi> LORDE <hi>is my ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herde, I ſhall lacke nothynge.</hi> Theſe are hyr weapens and go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wherwith ſhe hath hetherto ſmytten &amp; ouercome all hyr ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, and after the ſame maner ſhall ſhe haue the victorye ſtyll vnto domes daye.</p>
                     <p>The more alſo that the deuell and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde doth hurt &amp; vexe her, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better is it with her. For hyr edifyenge and increace ſtondeth in perſecucion, affliction, and death. Out of thys occaſion dyd one of the olde fathers ſaye: The bloud of martyrs is a ſede,<note place="margin">A notable ſayenge</note> where one is caſte, there ryſe an hundreth vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Of thys wonderfull victory ſynge certayne Pſalmes, as the .ix. x. &amp;c. After thys ſame maner haue I alſo (thorowe the grace of God) behaued my ſelfe thys eygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene yeare:<note place="margin">The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this boke</note> I haue euer ſuffred myne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes to be wroth, to threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to blaſpheme and condemne me, to caſt theyr heades ſtyll agaynſt me, to ymagin many euell wayes, &amp; to vſe diuerſe vnthryftye poyntes. I haue ſuffred them to take wonderous greate thought howe they myght deſtroye me and myne (yee gods) doctrine. Morouer I haue ben glad and merye (but more at one tyme then at another,) and not greatly regarded
<pb facs="tcp:4561:33"/>theyr ragynge, &amp; madneſſe, but haue holden me by the ſtaf of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, and had recourſe vnto the LORDES table. That is: I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe vnto God, wherin he hath ſo led me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue optayned all my wil and mynde. And in the meane tyme haue I done lytle or nothinge, but ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto hym a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter, or ſome lytle Pſalme. This is al my harneſſe, wherwith I haue defended me hetherto, not only agaynſt myne enemyes. but alſo thorow the grace of god, brought ſo much to paſſe, that whan I loke behynde me, &amp; call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce how it hath ſtond in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtrye, I do eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wonder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter is come ſo farre. I wold neuer haue thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the tenth parte ſhulde haue come to paſſe as it is now before oure eyes. He that hath begon it, ſhal brynge it well to an ende. Yee though nyne helles and worldes were ſet on an heap together agaynſt it. Let euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten man therfore learne thys ſcience, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hold hym by this ſtaf &amp; ſhepehooke, &amp; reſort vnto this table, whan heuyneſſe, or ony other myſfortune is at hande. And ſo ſhall he (doutles) receaue ſtrength &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte agaynſte euery thyng that oppreſſeth hym.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>The ſecond ſimilitude is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherof ther is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made ofttymes in the holy ſcripture. It was ſome precious oyle,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:33"/>as Balme, or els ſom other ſwete ſmellinge water, &amp; the vſe was to anoynte the kynges &amp; preſtes withal. Whan the Iewes alſo held theyr ſolemne feaſtes, and were diſpoſed to be mery, they dyd anoynte or ſprenkle them ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch precious oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as Chriſte declared lykewyſe in the ſixte of Mathewe, wher he ſayeth: whan thou faſteſt, anoynte thyne heade, and waſh thy face, &amp;c. The vſe then of this oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was had among thoſe people, whan they were diſpoſed to be mery &amp; glad. Lyke as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magdalene alſo thought to make the LORDE mery, whan ſhe poured vpon hys heade the precious water of Nardus, for ſhe ſawe that he was heuy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The full cuppe.</note>The thyrde ſimilitude is of the cuppe, which they broughte in theyr Gods ſeruice, whan they offered drynke offerynges, and were merye before the LORDE. Wyth theſe wordes then: <hi>Thou anoynteſt my head with oyle,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The ryche comfort of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </note>
                        <hi>and filleſt my cuppe ful</hi> wyll the prophete deſcrybe the greate ryche comforte which they that are faythfull haue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God, ſo that theyr conſciences are quyete, glad, and at reſt in the myddes of all tentacions and troubles. Yee euen of death. As yf he wold ſaye: doutleſſe the LOR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DE maketh me a maruaylous man of warre, and harneſſeth me wonderouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:4561:34"/>myne enemyes. I thought he ſhulde haue put materiall harneſſe vpon me, ſet an helmet vpon myne heade, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me aſweard in my hande, &amp; haue warned me to be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, &amp; to take diligent hede to my matter, leſt myne enemyes ſhulde ouertake me.</p>
                     <p>Nowe commeth he and ſetteth me downe at a table, and prepareth me a goodly banket, anoynteth myne heade with precious Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Or (after the maner of our contry) ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a garlande vpon myne heade, as yf I ſhulde go to ſome paſtyme or dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſynge, and not fyght with myne enemyes. And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that ther ſhulde be no ſcarceneſſe, he fyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth my cuppe full, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye drynke, make, good chere, &amp; be dronken. The table the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared is my harneſſe, the precious oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is my helmet, &amp; the ful cuppe is my ſweard, With theſe do I ouercome all myne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Is not this a maruailous preparyng to warre, &amp; yet a more wonderfull victory? Thus wyll he ſaye: LORDE, thy geſtes. whiche, ſyt at thy table, that is to ſaye, the faythfull ſhall not onely be ſtronge and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaunt giauntes agaynſt al theyr enemyes, but they ſhalbe mery alſo and dronken.<note place="margin">Spiritual dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe</note> For why? thou makeſt them good chere, as a ryche hooft vſeth to do to his geſtes: thou fedeſt them well, thou makeſt them luſty &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:4561:34"/>glad, thou fylleſt into them ſo muche, that they muſt nedes be dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is al done by the worde of grace. For by the ſame doth the LORDE oure ſhepherde fede and ſtrength ſo the hartes of his faythfull, that they dare defye al theyr enemyes, and ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophete: I am not afrayed for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of the people that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe me rounde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aboute. Pſalme. iii. And here afore in the fourth verſe: I fear no euell, for thou LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE art with me. With this (yee euen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ſame) worde, doth he geue them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the holy gooſt, whiche maketh them not onely to take good ſtomackes vnto them, &amp; to be of good corage, but ſo quyet alſo in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues and mery, that for the ſame great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceadynge ioye, they are euen dronken.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">This muſt be ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande.</note>He ſpeaketh here then of a ſpirytuall ſtrength, of a ſpirituall myrth, and of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, which is a godly ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth Rom. i. A ioye (as ſaynt Paul calleth it) in the holy gooſt. Rom. xiiii. And a bleſſed dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenneſſe, whan people are not full of wyne, (wherout followeth inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience,) but full of the holy gooſt. Ephe. v. This is the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; the weapens, wherwith our LORD God prepareth his faythfull agaynſt the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell and the worlde, namely, in theyr mouth geueth he them hys worde, and in theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4561:35"/>harte he geueth corage, that is to ſaye, the holy gooſte. Wyth ſuche ordinaunce put they from them all feare, and wyth glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bukle they wyth all theyr enemyes, ſmyte them, and ouercome them with all theyr myght, wyſedome, and holyneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Such ſouldyers were the Apoſtels on whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſondaye, whan they went vp to Ieruſalem agaynſte the commaundement of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure and the hye preſtes (and ordred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, as yf they had ben very goddes, and all the other but greſhoppers) and went e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thorowe with all power and ioye, as yf they had bene dronken. In ſo muche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſome had them in deriſion therfore, &amp; ſayd: They were full of ſwete wyne. Neuertheleſſe S. Peter declared out of the prophet Ioel, that they were not full of ſwete wyne, but ful of the holy gooſt. And ſo he ſmote aboute hym with hys ſwearde, that is: he opened his mouth, and preached the worde of God, and felled downe thre thouſande ſoules at once from the power of the deuell. Actu. ii.</p>
                     <p>This ſtrength, ioye, and bleſſed dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe doth not onely ſhewe it ſelfe in the faythfull, whan they be in proſperite &amp; haue peace, but alſo whan they ſuffre and dye.</p>
                     <p>As whan the counſell at Ieruſalem cauſed the Apoſtles to be beaten, they were glad of
<pb facs="tcp:4561:35"/>it, that they were worthy to ſuffre rebuke for the name of Chriſte, Actu. v. And in the v. to the Romaynes doth ſaynt Paule ſay: We reioyce alſo in troubles. &amp;c. Afterwarde were ther many martyrs alſo,<note place="margin">The ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt &amp; ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hartes of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue fuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred death for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God.</note> whiche with mery harte and laughynge mouthes wente vnto theyr death, as yf they had gone to ſomepaſtyme or daunce: Lyke as we reade of ſaynt Agnes, and ſaynt Agatha (whyche were virgins .xiii. or .xiiii. yeare olde,) and of other mo, whiche were of ſuche inwarde corage and confydence, that they dyd not onely ouercome the deuell and the worlde by theyr death, but alſo made good chere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then with theyr hartes, as though they had ben dronken of very ioye. And this gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the deuell excedynge ſore, namely, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men are at ſuche quyetneſſe in them ſelues, that they deſpyſe his great myght and gyle. In our tyme alſo haue ther be many which for the knowlege of Chriſte haue bene glad to ſuffre death. We ſe more ouer that ther be many, whyche wyth perfecte vnderſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and fayth dye vpon theyr beddes, and ſaye wyth Simeon: LORDE, now letteſt thou thy ſeruaunt departe in peace, &amp;c. that it is a ioye to beholde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of whom I haue ſene many my ſelfe. And all thys commeth becauſe that (as the prophete ſayeth) they
<pb facs="tcp:4561:36"/>be anoynted with the oyle, whiche the .xliiii. Pſalme calleth the oyle of gladneſſe, and becauſe they haue dronke of the full cnppe whiche the LORDE hath fylled.</p>
                     <p>Yee but thou wylt ſaye:<note place="margin">Obiection</note> I fele not my ſelfe yet ſo apte, that I coulde be content to dye. &amp;c. That maketh no matter.<note place="margin">Anſwere.</note> Dauid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo (as it is ſayd afore) hath not bene ſure of that ſcience at all houres, but ſomtyme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned that he was caſt out of gods ſyght. Other holy men alſo haue not alwaye had an hartye confidence towarde God, and a perpetuall delyte and pacience in theyr troubles and temptacions.<note place="margin">Note this well.</note> Saynt Paul ſomtyme is ſo ſure &amp; certayne in hym ſelfe, and maketh ſuche boaſt of Chriſte, that he careth not for the curſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, for ſynne, death, nor for the deuell. I lyue not nowe (ſayeth he. Galat. ii.) but Chriſte lyueth in me. Item: I deſyre to be lowſed and to be with Chriſt. Phil i. Item: Who ſhall ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from the loue of God, whiche ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not is owne ſonne, but hath geuen hym for vs all? How ſhall he not with hym geue vs al thynges alſo? Shal trouble, anguyſh, perſecucion, ſwearde, &amp;c. ſeparate vs from hym? Ro. viii. There ſpeaketh he of death, of the deuell, and of all euell with ſuche a corage, as yf he were the ſtrongeſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:4561:36"/>of all ſayntes, vnto whom death were but aſporte. But incontinently in another place, he ſpeaketh as thoughe he were the weakeſt and greateſt ſynner vpon earth. i. Cor. ii. I was with you (ſayeth he,) in weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, in feare, and in muche tremblynge. I am carnall, ſolde vnder ſynne, and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the lawe of ſynne, whiche is in my membres. O wretched man that I am, who ſhall delyuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body of this death? Roma. vii. And in the fyfth to the Galath. he teacheth that in the ſayntes of God ther is a continual ſtryfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe agaynſt the ſprete. &amp;c. Therfore oughteſt thou not imme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatly to diſpayre, though thou feleſt thy ſelfe feble and fayntharted, but praye dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently that thou mayeſt endure by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde, and increace in the fayth and knowlege of Chriſt. As the prophete doth here, &amp; teacheth other men lykewyſe ſo to do, and ſayeth:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Oh let thy louynge kyndneſſe and mercy followe me all the dayes of my lyfe, that I maye dwell in the houſe of the</hi> LORDE <hi>for euer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For as muche as the deuell neuer ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to plage the faythfull inwardly with feare, outwardely wyth deceatfulneſſe of falſe doctours or teachers, and with the vio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lence of tyrauntes: he prayeth here therfore
<pb facs="tcp:4561:37"/>at the ende earneſtly, that God which hath geuen hym this treaſure, wyl kepe hym faſt by it alſo vnto the ende. And ſayeth: O gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyous God ſhewe me ſuch fauour, that thy louynge kyndneſſe and mercy maye followe me all the dayes of my lyfe.<note place="margin">Why the prophet maketh this prayer.</note> And immediat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly he declareth what he calleth this louynge kynoneſſe and mercy, namely, that he maye remayne in the houſe of the LORDE for euer. As yf he wolde ſaye: Thou haſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne the matter, thou haſt geuen me thy holy worde, and accepted me amonge them that are thy people, whyche do knowlege, prayſe and geue thankes vnto the, graunt me therfore ſuch grace from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forth, that I maye continue ſtyll by the ſame worde, &amp; neuer to be ſeparated more from thy holy Chriſten flocke. Thus doth he praye alſo in the .xxvi. Pſalme. One thinge (ſayeth he) haue I deſyred of the LORDE, whyche I wolde fayne haue: namely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye dwell in the houſe of the LORDE al the dayes of my lyfe, to beholde the fayre bewty of the LORDE (that is to ſaye, the true ſeruyce of God) and to vyſite his temple.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A notable enſample.</note>The prophete then here by his enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple teacheth and exhorteth all ſuche as put theyr truſt in God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be not careleſſe, proude, or preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous in them ſelues, but
<pb facs="tcp:4561:37"/>to feare and geue them ſelues vnto prayer, that they leſe not this treaſure. And dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe this earneſt exhortacion ſhulde ſteare vs vp, and make vs feruent vnto diligent prayer. For ſeynge that holy Dauid whiche was a prophete, ſo hyghly endued with all maner of godly wyſedome and knowlege, and with diuerſe greate excellent gyftes of God. Seynge he (I ſaye) dyd praye ſo ofte and with ſuch great earneſt, that he myghte abyde by thys treaſure. Much more ſhall it be mete for vs (whiche are vtterly nothynge to be compared vnto hym,<note place="margin">We haue moſt nede to watch &amp; praye.</note> and lyue alſo nowe at the ende of the worlde, whan as Chriſte and the Apoſtles ſaye, it ſhalbe an horryble and peryllous tyme,) it ſhalbe muche more conuenient (I ſaye) to watch and praye wyth all earneſt and diligence, that we maye contynue in the houſe of the LORDE all the dayes of oure lyfe, name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, that we maye heare the worde of God, and receaue the manyfolde commodityes and frutes that come of it, (as it reharſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) and continue in the ſame vnto the ende. Which graunte vs Chriſt, our onely ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herde and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueoure.</p>
                     <closer>AMEN.</closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:38"/>
                  <p>¶ How and whether a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to flye the horryble plage of the <hi>Peſtilence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ A ſermon out of the .xci. Pſalme</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Qui habitat in adiuto.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>By Andrewe Oſlander.</p>
                  <p>¶ Tranſlated out of hygh Almayne into Englyſhe.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:39"/>
                  <head>¶ A Sermon out of the Pſalme, Qui habitat. &amp;c. how and vnto what place a Chriſten man ought to flye the horrible plage of the peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much as Almyghty God doth vyſet, handle, and punyſſhe the contry and region wyth the horrible and fearfull plage of the peſtilence, and many folkes (after an vnma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerly faſhion) are ſo afrayed therof, that ther be herde and ſene of them all maner of vncoſtumable wordes and workes, whiche become not well a Chriſten man: And ſeynge that all the dedes of charite whyche one Chriſten man is bounde to ſhewe vnto another (no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto Chriſt him ſelfe,) are perlouſly omytted, wherby then ryſeth all maner of ſklaunder to the weake, and myſreporte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Goſpell: I thought it profitable and neceſſary to beſtowe vpon youre charite in this caſe a ſhorte inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and comforte out of the holy ſcripture, to the intent that the ignoraunt maye be taughte, the weake ſtrengthed, and euery one counſelled after hys callynge to ſerue his neghbour. And I wyll take for me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xci. Pſalme, which ſoundeth after this maner:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4561:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Who ſo ſytteth vnder the defence of the hygheſt, and abydeth vnder the ſhadowe of the Almyghtye,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſayeth vnto the</hi> LORDE: <hi>My hope, and my ſtronge holde: my God on whom I truſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For he delyuereth me from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noy ſome peſtilence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall couer the wyth hys fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and thy truſte ſhalbe vnder hys wynges: hys truth is ſpeare and ſhylde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So that thou nedeſt not to fear for the horrybleneſſe of the nyghte, for the aro wes that flye by daye tyme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the peſtilence that commenth preuely in the darke, for the ſyckeneſſe that deſtroyeth in the noone daye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Though a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fall at thy ſyde, and ten thouſande at thy ryght hande, yet ſhall it not come nye the.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yee wyth thyne eyesſhalte thou ſe thy deſyre, and beholde, howethe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ſhalbe rewarded.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4561:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt afore we come to the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of theſe comfortable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, your charite ſhal fyrſt knowe that it is not my meanyng to for byd or inhibite ony man to flye or to vſe phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſycke, or to auoyde daungerous and ſycke places in theſe fearfull ayres,<note place="margin">What ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes retayn a man in daungero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us places.</note> ſo farre as a man doth not therin agaynſt the belefe, nor Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, nor agaynſt his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, nor agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of his neghboure. For though ſome wyl ſaye: Such plage tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth no man, but thoſe that be ordeyned of God therevnto, lyke as ther be certayne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples therof fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in the holy ſcripture: Namely how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ezech. <hi>9.</hi> and Apoca .vii. ther was ſent an angel, which aforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de marked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertuous &amp; electe, or euer it was charged &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeconde angell to ſmyte (with peſtilence or other plages) thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were not marked. Neuertheles agaynſt that it myght be ſayde: Good ſyr, thoughe it wente ſo at ſuche a tyme in ſuche places, who maketh vs ſure yet nowe, that it ſhall therfore chaunce ſo in all other deathes of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? Therfore wyll I now at this tyme let all ſuche thynges continue in theyr worthy neſſe and fre, lyke as other natural thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, whiche be ſubiecte and committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to oure reaſon to rule. But as for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>whiche (by reaſon of offyce, or for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte ſake, or for other reaſonable cauſes) can not, or be not mynded to flye, I wyll here withall ſhewe them theyr beſt and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gheſt comforte that they haue.</p>
                  <p>In lyke maner, I wyll not entre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them, that ſpeake naturally therof: and ſaye:<note place="margin">The cauſe of peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and lyke diſeaſes.</note> Suche plage commeth out of the influence of the ſtarres, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workynge of the Cometes, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſeaaſonable we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and alterynge of the ayre, out of the Southe wyndes, out of ſtynkynge waters, or out of foule myſtes of the grounde: For ſuch wyſedome of theyrs wyll we leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them vndeſpyſed, and not fyght there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt: But (as Chriſten men) we wyll holde vs vnto the worde of God, the ſame wyll we ſuffre to be oure mooſt hye wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and geue crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto it, and follow it: and ſo ſhall we fynde muche better and ſurer inſtruccion: Namley,<note place="margin">The chefe cauſes of peſtilence is Gods wrath.</note> that this horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble plage of the peſtilence commeth out of Gods wrath, becauſe of the deſpyſyge and tranſgreſſynge of his godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. For thus ſayeth the holy prophete Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the fyft boke, the .xxviii. Chapter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yf thou wylt not herken vnto the voyce of the</hi> LORDE <hi>thy God, to obſerue and kepe all hys commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes
<pb facs="tcp:4561:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ordinaunces whiche I commaunde the, then ſhal all theſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes come vpon the,</hi> &amp;c. And it followeth: <hi>The</hi> LORDE <hi>ſhall cauſe the peſtilence to endure longe wyth the: the</hi> LORDE <hi>ſhall ſmyte the wyth ſwellynge, feuer, heate, burnynge, blaſtynge, drouth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall perſecute the tyll he vtterly deſtroye the, and brynge the to naught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And certaynly this is the playne truth and the very originall of theſe plages. No man ought to doute theron. For thoughe the forſayd natural cauſes do ſomwhat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thereto, yet is it ſure and vndouted, that the ſame cauſes be ſent and ſteared vp oute of Gods wrath for our ſynne and vnthank fulneſſe. And truely that it is euen ſo, the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcripture declareth, not wych bare wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des onely, but ſheweth it alſo wyth notable enſamples. For in the fourth boke of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the fourtenth Chapter, whan all the ſpyes (excepte Ioſua and Caleb) ſpake euell of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of promyſe, and made the people vnpaciente and vprouryſſhe, ſo that they choſe them a captayne, and thought to go agayne into Egypte, and to ſtone Moſes and Aaron, (which commaunded them the contrarye) we reade thus: Then appeared the glorye of the LORDE, and ſpake vnto
<pb facs="tcp:4561:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>Moſes: Howe longe doth thys people blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme me? And howe longe wyll they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue me, for all the tokens that I haue done vpon them: therfore wyll I ſmytte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye them with peſtilence, and make of the a grater nacion then thys.</p>
                  <p>Lykewyſe alſo whan Dauid cauſed the people to be nombred agaynſte Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he diſpleaſed the LORDE God horibly therwith. Therfore layed he the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhment vpon hym, ſo that he was fayne to choſe hym ſelfe whether he had rather haue, ſeuen yeares derth, or thre monethes myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce in battayl, or thre dayes peſtilence in the lande. And whan he choſe the peſtilence, ther dyed in thre dayes ſeuentye thouſande men, as it is wrytten in the laſte Chapter of the .ii. boke of Samuel.</p>
                  <p>Seynge then that out of the word of God we knowe the very cauſe of thys horryble plage: Namely, that it is the defaute of our ſynnes, as vnbelefe, diſobedience &amp; vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: therfore before all thynges it ſhall be neceſſary, that we refrayne from the ſame, repent, and aniende our lyues. Yf we wyll els be preſerued and delyuered from thys hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible plage. For yf God punyſh vs becauſe of ſynne, it is good to conſydre that we muſt fyrſt knowlege and eſchue our ſynnes, in caſe
<pb facs="tcp:4561:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he ſhall withdrawe and take awaychys wrath &amp; punyſhment from vs.<note place="margin">Yf we ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de not God conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nueth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſhynge.</note> For yf we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in our euell, ſynfull, and culpable lyfe, certaynly he ſhal not ceaſſe with the punyſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, but go forth more &amp; more, tyll he geue and recompence accordynge to our workes. But yf we knowlege our ſynne, refrayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, repent, and axe grace, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall he alſo take awaye hys wrath. And thys horrible wrath (with other heuy burthens as warre &amp; derth that lye vpon oure neck) ſhall he mercyfully take away from vs agayne. As holy Paule ſayeth .i. Cor. xi. Yf we iudged our ſelues, we ſhulde not be iudged: But whan we are iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged, we be chaſtened of the LORDE, that we ſhulde not be damned with the worlde.</p>
                  <p>And out of all thys maye youre charyte well perceaue, howe vnwyſely and vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenly they do, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out of inordinate feare, of thys plage leaue theyr callynge and offyce, maliciouſly wythdrawyng the loue, helpe, &amp; faythfulneſſe, which they (out of gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement) are bounde to ſhewe vnto theyr neghbours, and ſo do ſynne greuouſly agaynſt the commaundement of God. For certaynly they do but ſteare vp the wrath of God more earneſtly agaynſte themſelues, that he may the ſooner take hold vpon them, and pluck them awaye with thys plage. For
<pb facs="tcp:4561:42"/>men maye heare on euery ſyde,<note place="margin">A pyteous caſe.</note> that ſome do ſhone and flye not only the ſyck, but alſo the whole: Yee (that yet more foolyſhe is) euen the platters and candelſtyches whiche come out of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge houſes, as though death dyd ſurely ſtyck therin. And (out of ſuche fonde chyldyſhe feare) it commeth, that not onely ſome ſyck folkes be ſuffred to dye away with out all kepynge, helpe, and comforte, but the wemen alſo greate wyth chylde be forſaken in theyr nede, or els commeth there vtterly no man vnto them. Yee a man maye heare alſo, that the chyldren forſake theyr fathers and mothers, and one houſhold body kepeth hymſelfe awaye from another, and ſheweth no ſoue vnto hym: Whyche neuertheles he wolde be glad to ſe ſhewed vnto hymſelfe, yf he laye in lyke neceſſite.</p>
                  <p>Howbeyt I ſuppoſe ther come not manye ſuch chaunces to paſſe, neuertheleſſe I muſt ſpeake therof that it be done nomore from henceforth. For certaynly it is vnwyſely &amp; vnchriſtenly handled: &amp; we nede not thynke that the ſame is the waye to eſcape thys plage, but rather an occaſion that it raygne the more myghtely ouer vs.<note place="margin">The more we flye the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, the farther daunger we ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in</note> For ſeynge it is ſure (as ye haue herde afore) that ſuch plage is ſent for punyſhment of oure ſynnes, and Chriſte hath geuen vs a new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:4561:43"/>that we ſhulde loue one another (as he hath loued vs) it followeth, that the farther we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from the loue of our neghboure, the more we lade ſynne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, and deſerue thys plage but the more. Agayne the more dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye that we take hede vnto the loue of oure neghboure, the ſurer ſhall we be from thys plage: No man nedeth to doute therof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Noman ought to preaſſe in the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger wythout neceſſite.</note>But here wythall wyll I alſo counſell or compell no man, to ony vnuedeful daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, (that he is not bounde vnto by his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, nor by loue,) but onely warne thoſe, whyche for feare leaue that whiche they are bounde to do before God: To the intent that for ſuche naked feares ſake, they do not tranſgreſſe nor omytte the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, &amp; hope by ſynne to eſcape this plage, which neuertheleſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth becauſe of ſynne. For that were a foolyſh vnaduyſed counſel, yf one wolde go aboute to eſcape the wrath of God by tranſgreſſion, and by ſynne to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the punyſhment of ſynne.</p>
                  <p>Beſydes thys, doth experience ſhewe alſo that they which be ſo ſore afrayed, do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly miſcary. Agayne, they that wayte vpon theyr offyces and ſerue theyr neghbours, be delyuered: As it is well ſene in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minyſters of the churche and other mo, that ſhone not the ſyck, but muſte vyſet and comforte them
<pb facs="tcp:4561:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>wyth Gods worde, and prouyde for them wyth the holy ſacrament: For we ſe no where, that they therfore muſt alſo be ſoone ſyck and muſt dye. Yee how muſt the hygher powers of the worlde do, which (by reaſon of theyr callynge, and for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune profyt &amp; regimentes ſake) abyde alſo in the ioperdy, and muſt mynyſtre becauſe of loue: Specy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefeſt, on one wherof ther lyeth more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of other? And yet doth God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munly preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be delyuered left ſtyl on lyue, and dye in a good quyet age.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelefe and miſt ruſt in God is cauſe of flyenge</note>Therfore certaynly ſuch inordinate feare and flyenge agaynſt Gods commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is nothynge els, but a declaryng of a greate and ſore vnbelefe, that men do not beleue and truſt in God, that he can and wyll delyuer. And thus is verifyed the ſayenge: <hi>The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly haue no peace.</hi> Eſay. lvii. For yf we wyll feare and flye where no parell is, whan wyll we then beſtowe oure lyues for oure neghbours, as Chriſt hath done for vs? &amp; we alſo be bounde to do lykewyſe .i. Io. iii.</p>
                  <p>Who ſo now deſyreth to eſcape y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of God &amp; thys horrible plage, let hym not axe his own reaſon how he ſhal do, but beleue &amp; follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God: which teacheth hym, not to flye euell ayre &amp; infecte places (which he maye well do: neuertheleſſe he remayneth
<pb facs="tcp:4561:44"/>yet vncertayne wheter it helpeth or no) but it teacheth hym to leaue of from ſynne, as from the very originall cauſe of thys plage and punyſhment, and (by true repentaunce and amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyuyng) to walke agayne in the ryght waye. For y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the onely ſure &amp; wholſome flyenge in thys dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous tyme, wherby a man may eſcape thys plage.</p>
                  <p>But whyther a man ought to flye, therof wyll we heare the holy gooſte by the prophete in thys pſalm. He knoweth it much better then we can thynke, and ſayeth after thys maner:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who ſo ſytteth vnder the defence of the hygheſt, and abydeth vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do we of the almyghtye. He ſayeth vnto the</hi> LORDE: <hi>My hope, and my ſtronge holde: My God on Whom I hope. For he delyuereth me from the ſnare of the hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and from the noyſome peſtilence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe wordes (my moſte dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) ſhall ye take to hart, and marke them well wyth all diligence: For they be not the wordes of men whyche can lye and deceaue. Hewbeyt though they were mens wordes, &amp; ſome olde wyſe man ſpake them (or ſome well learned phyſician) ye wolde not yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyſe them, but receaue and kepe them. But now be they the very wordes of the hye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye
<pb facs="tcp:4561:44"/>of God, which the holy gooſt ſpeaketh by the mouth of the prophete. And they teach vs whether we ought to flye for thys plage, that we maye be ſafe. And certaynly they muſt nedes be the very truth: For heauen and earth muſt paſſe, but my wordes ſhall not paſſe, ſayeth the LORDE.</p>
                  <p>But that ye maye vnderſtande them ryght and well, ye ſhall remembre, that it is the vſe of the holy ſcripture (ſpecially in the pſalmes) to declare one meanynge with two maner of ſayenges, as ye haue oft tymes herde. For ſo doth the prophete here &amp; ſayeth: <hi>Who ſo ſytteth vnder the defence of the hygheſt, and abydeth vnder the ſhadow of the almyghtye.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">To ſyt vnder the defence of the hygheſt</note> For to ſyt vnder the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the hygheſt, is euen as much to ſaye, as to abyde vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadow of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almyghtie. And with theſe wordes meaneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet nothynge els, but: who ſo putteth hys truſte in God with aryght ſure Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe, &amp; geueth hymſelfe ouer into his protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and defence, (For ſuch people doth God receaue to grace) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holdeth he for his owne deare chyldren, (and euen ſo they be) and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them his holy ſprete, whiche worketh in them very ſaluacion and godly workes.</p>
                  <p>Therfore remayneth he alſo vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, and all thynges muſt ſerue for theyr wealth, as
<pb facs="tcp:4561:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>Paule ſayeth Rom. viii. Suche proteccion alſo and defence of God, is ſet forth vnto vs euery where in the ſcripture, as an ouerſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowyng &amp; coueryng with wynges. For lyke as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two Cherubins ſpred out theyr winges ouer the Arke: Exod. xxxvii. Euen ſo doth God ſprede out the wynges of hys protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer hys electe. Therfore ſayeth Moſes Deuter. xxxii. Lyke as an Aegle ſteareth vp hys neſt, and flyeth ouer hys yonge ones: ſo ſpredde he out hys fethers, and bare hys people vpon hys wynges. After this maner ſpake the holy angell Gabriell alſo vnto the mooſte bleſſed and pure virgyn Mary, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſhulde be the mother of God: The holy gooſt ſhall come vpon the, and the power of the hygheſt ſhall ouerſhadowe the Luc. i. In lyke maner ſpake Chriſt alſo vnto Jeruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: How oft wolde I haue gathered thy chyldren together, as an henne gathereth hyr chekens vnder hir winges, &amp; ye wold not? Mat. xxiii. For though a true beſeuyng man be in dede the temple of God, &amp; God dwelleth in hym: yet vſeth the ſcripture oft to ſpeak therof, as though he dyd flye aboue vs (in aſmuche as he doth ouerſhadow, couer, &amp; defende vs:) and that becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauen and the heauen of all heauens (as Salomon ſayeth) can not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende nor conteyn hym .iii. Reg. iii. But
<pb facs="tcp:4561:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>though he dwelleth in vs, yet flyeth he wyde, hye and lowe, not only on the outſyde of vs, but alſo on the outſyde and ouer all creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. And ſo in all theſe wordes ther is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge els ſayde, but: who ſo euer is a ryght beleuynge Chriſten.</p>
                  <p>Marke nowe then that he ſayeth not: Who ſo is wyſe, ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, ryche, whole, or well frended. Nother ſayeth he alſo: who ſo kepeth hym ſelfe thence, or flyeth thether, holdeth hym ſelfe well, or vſeth good phiſycke: but who ſo putteth hys truſt in God. Not that the foreſayd good thynges be euell, or maye not be had or vſed wyth profyte: But that they (where fayth is not) may euen as ſoone do harme as good, are in no wyſe able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer from the wrath of God. But what doth the beleuer: He ſayeth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE <hi>my hope.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">They that miſvſe Gods cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual whor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome.</note> But this do not the vngodly and vnbeleuers, but ſet theyr hope in the forſayd poyntes, put theyr truſt in them, and boaſt theron, and ſo commyt ſpiritual whoredom therwith, and make ydols therof. But to God do not they lyfte vp theyr eyes, nother thynke they vpon hym, nor feare hym. And whan he commeth then with hys wrath, and ouertaketh them wyth a plage, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite they muſt nedes thynke vpon hym: than feare they, and be afrayed of hym, flye away,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>and knowe not where to abyde. Then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſheth awaye theyr hope and boaſtynge, whych they (in tyme of proſperite) had vnto the creatures.<note place="margin">Horrible is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath and ende of the vnrygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</note> And ſo commeth it to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr wyſedome hath ben playne foolyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: theyr ſtrength, theyr own myſfortune: theyr ryches, theyr owne deſtruccion: theyr health, theyr owne harme: theyr fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, theyr owne ypocrytes &amp; traytours.<note place="margin">Sapie. iii. ‡ Jo. viii, a Pſal. i. b Pro. x. a. and. xi. a Ecclſ. v, b Jacob. i. b</note> ‡ And all that whyche they truſted vnto, can not helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whan they wolde hyde themſelues on the backſyde therof, it is euen as much as whan one hydeth hym behynde a ladder. And whan they wolde ſeke helpe thereby, it is euen lyke as yf a wolfe ſhuld defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a ſhepe or a gooſe.</p>
                  <p>But thus goeth it not wyth the bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: for who ſo putteth hys truſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE, ſhal not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded. Therfore ſayeth he not only that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE is his hope, but alſo hys ſtronge holde, whyche he maye flye vnto, in the whyche he maye ſhutte hymſelfe cloſe, and be delyuered therin. As Salomon ſayeth in the .xviii. chapter of the Prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes: The name of the LORDE is a ſtronge caſtel, the ryghteous flyeth vnto it, and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnbeleuers haue theyr hope euen in theyr goodes, but in neceſſyte they fynde not refuge, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful hath a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge holde and hye caſtell in God the LORDE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4561:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <note place="margin">Extrema gaudii luctus oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupat.</note>And though the vnbeleuers haue theyr whole wyll all theyr lyfe longe, yet hath it an euell ende, as it had wyth the rych man, whych was buryed in the hell. Luce. xvi. For who ſo beleueth not, ſhalbe damned. Agayn, though the faythfull be plaged and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all hys lyfe longe, ſo that he can not ſe how he maye be delyuered, yet hath he thys comforce, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE is hys God: that is, that he can helpe &amp; delyuer hym as an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty LORDE, yee after ſuche a faſhion &amp; waye, as nother he hymſelfe, nor ony mans reaſon can thynke or deuyſe. And thoughe he do it not, yet doth not the faythfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre, but letteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE be his God, on whom he hopeth: that is, at whoſe hande he loketh for al good in the lyfe for to come and euerlaſtynge. For hope ſeyth and loketh on that whych is to come, whych as yet is hyd. As Paule ſayeth Roma. the .viii. Chapter. Hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſene, is no hope for how can a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is ſene. But yf we hope that which we ſe not, we loke for it by pacience.</p>
                  <p>And ſo is this meanyng: The vnbeleuers haue theyr hope in the creatures, and are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayed of God.<note place="margin">The fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full is lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of all creatures.</note> The faythfull hath his hope to God, and is lorde ouer the creatures. The vnbeleuers myſcary, and by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures fynde they no helpe in nede. The
<pb facs="tcp:4561:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>faythfull myſcary not, but God is vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtronge holde. The vnbeleuers maye well haue theyr wylles as longe as they lyue, but at the laſt (thorow theyr diſpayre) ther follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth euerlaſtynge daſtinacion. The fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may theyr lyfe longe haue diſquyetneſſe and tentacion, but at the laſt (thorow theyr hope) ther followeth euerlaſtynge lyfe.</p>
                  <p>Suche hope ſhulde they haue, and they haue it in dede, that though they muſt lye vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der as longe as they lyue, yet after death they ſhall enherete euerlaſtynge lyfe.. But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly it commeth not to paſſe, that they muſt alwaye lye vnder: For God is fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſuffreth not his to be temted aboue theyr ſtrength, but maketh the temtacion ſo to haue an ende, that we may bear it .i. Cor. x. Therfore ſayeth the prophete moreouer:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For he delyuereth me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſnare of the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the noyſome peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> And in theſe wordes doth he ſhortly ſhewe vnto vs, that almyghty God can and wyll delyuer his owne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all miſfortune yet euen in this lyfe.<note place="margin">Two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunces.</note> For al the myſchaunces that we be troubled wythall in thys temporall lyfe, are of two ſortes: Some come out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deuyce of the deuell and of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as ſhame and perſecucion. Some playnly of nature and out of the ordinaunce of God, as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt
<pb facs="tcp:4561:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>and peſtilence. The faythfull nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth and maketh hys boaſt, that theſe myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunces can not be ſo greate and myghtye, but God ſhall delyuer hym there from.</p>
                  <p>And it is a goodly naturall ſimilitude, that he lykeneth the euell and wycked deuyce of the vngodly agaynſte the faythfull,<note place="margin">The ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto a hunter.</note> to a nette or ſnare of the hunter. For lyke as an hunter proueth the kynde and nature of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery wylde beaſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth pryuely after hym, ſeketh out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe &amp; habitacion therof, and afterwarde ſetteth the nette, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may dryue it therin: Euen ſo do the vngodly alſo vnto the ryghteous. Fyrſt, they loke how they be mynded. Yf ony one be fre of langage, then ſet they hym on fyre that he may ſpeake ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>what ſharpely, as ſaynt Steuen dyd. Actu. the .vii. Chapter. Yf he be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle and frendly, then ymagen they ſome foolyſhe thynge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, and flatter awaye hys harte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, as Dalila dyd vnto Samſon.<note place="margin">Iudi. xvi.</note> Yf he ſeke the ſaluacion of the people, then ſklaunder they hym,<note place="margin">Math, xi.</note> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes blaſphemed Chriſt to be a wyne ſupper and a companion of publica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Yf he be ſymple,<note place="margin">Pſal. cxxxix.</note> then lye they vpon hym be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde hys backe, or euer he be ware therof: Then followe they vpon hym, crye, lye, and complayne, that the vertuous Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man woteth not what poynte to be at, or how he
<pb facs="tcp:4561:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath deſerued it. Neuertheleſſe they thynke the bell is ſo caſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at the laſt it muſt rynge as they wyll, but it fayleth them.</p>
                  <p>For the LORDE on whom we beleue, which is our hope,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Cor. x. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i. Pet. ii.</note> refuge, and God, can not only preſerue vs from theyr ſnares that we fall not therin: but alſo whan we fall into them, and they thynke we be theyr captiues, he can and wyll delyuer vs yet therout. In lyke maner doth God the LORDE preſerue hys faythfull, not onely from the noyſome ſyckneſſe of the peſtilence, but alſo whan they be taken therwyth and infecte already, he delyuereth them from it, and maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whole agayne. But how that commeth to paſſe, and howe we ſhall vnderſtande it, it ſhall followe here after more clearely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Why the peſtilence is a noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneſſe.</note>Thys is nowe well to be marked alſo, that the peſtilence is a noyſome ſyckneſſe, not becauſe it bryngeth death: (for that do al other mortal ſyckneſſes lykewyſe, and death is no loſſe vnto the faythfull, but auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, as Paule ſayeth, Philip. the fyrſt Chapter) but becauſe that it taketh awaye the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple very ſodenly, vnloked for, and vnwares: Wherout the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther followeth, ſtryfe, lawyng, or buſyneſſe amonge ſynners, and of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune welth, as euery man by hymſelfe can lyghtely perceaue and vnderſtande. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:4561:48"/>is it alſo an horrible punyſhment ouer the ſynne of the worlde,<note place="margin">Peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible puny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhment.</note> whyche concerneth both them that dye, and them that are lefte alyue, as here after it ſhall followe.</p>
                  <p>Where as is nowe ſuche a fayth as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth credence vnto God, he ſhall preſerue hym from all wycked ymaginacions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lykewyſe from all noyſome ſyckeneſſes. And at the laſt ſhall he ſaue hym, that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not wythout frute, but breaketh out wyth ryght loue and faythfulneſſe towarde hys neghboure, and deſyreth alſo to brynge hym vnto that poynte, that he maye beleue and be partaker of all ſuche goodes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites of God. Therfore doth the prophete turne hys wordes now alſo vnto hys negh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, and ſayeth farthermore:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He ſhall couer the wyth hys fethers, and thyne hope ſhalbe vnder hys wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</hi> That is: Yf thou alſo wylt put thy truſt in hym, thou ſhalte fynde it ſo lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe. For he ſheweth ſuch his benefytes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all and euery one that put theyr truſte in hym. As for the couerynge of hys fethers, and hope vnder hys wynges, youre charite hath herde ynough afore what it is.</p>
                  <p>Now though all faythfull loke for ſuche helpe at God, and it happeneth vnto them, yet is it not done without a ſpeciall battayll
<pb facs="tcp:4561:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>of fayth. For ſuche helpe doth he promyſe vs in hys holy worde, that we ſhulde beleue it. And yf we beleue it, it happeneth vnto vs ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge to oure fayth. Therfore ſayeth the prophet more ouer: <hi>hys truth is ſpeare and ſhylde</hi> That is hys godly promyſes,<note place="margin">The vea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, of fayth</note> whych are ſure and true, &amp; notherlye nor deceaue: Thoſe be our weapens wherwyth we fyght, and ouercome all aduerſyte. But lyke as ſpeare &amp; ſhylde are not profytable vnto hym that can not vſe them, nor wyll: Euen ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo do not the promyſes of God profyte hym, that can not fyghte therwyth, and wyll not beleue theron. For that is the ryght ſcyence in this battayll whan myſfortune,<note place="margin">The ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the warre of fayth</note> aduerſite or tentacion commeth, that we loke aboute vs accordynge vnto Gods worde: Namely; what comforte and promyſe he hath made vnto vs in ſuche a caſe, &amp; wyth a ryghte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe to take holde of the ſame as of a ſhylde; and to comforte and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de oure ſelues ther with, ſo can ther no miſchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce do vs harme, as the holye Saynt Paule in the laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of hys Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Epheſians teacheth and ſayeth: Before all thynges take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhylde of fayth, wherwyth ye maye quenche all the fyrye dartes of the wycked, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Agaynſte the ſame (namelye agaynſte Sathan oure head enemye) is ſuche worde
<pb facs="tcp:4561:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God, euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghte ſpeare, wherwith we wounde and ouercome hym.<note place="margin">Nothynge hurteth the Deuell ſo ſore as the worde of God.</note> For no bodely wapen hurteth and hyndreth men ſo ſore, as the worde of God ſtoppeth and hyndreth Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than yf it be thruſt vnder hys noſe agaynſte hys venymous dealynge and temtacion. For yf a ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (that dealeth wrongeouſly and vnthriftely in hys mayſters goodes &amp; buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes) be afrayed, vexed, and perſed thorowe the harte, whan a ſymple man ſayeth vnto him: Thou vnthrift why dooſt thou ſo? that is not thy mayſters wyll and meanynge, he dyd not ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the. Howe much more goeth it thorowe Satans harte, whan a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Chriſten man holdeth the worde of God vnder hys eyes; and bryngeth witneſſe ouer hym, that he as a wycked creature ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth agaynſt hys maker, &amp; agaynſt hys cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen chyldren? Therfore doth holye ſaynte Paule call Gods worde alſo the ſwearde of the ſprete:<note place="margin">Mat. iiii.</note> And the LORDE Chriſte defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth hymſelfe onely wyth the ſame agaynſte all temtacions of Satan in the wylderneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Howe whan thou takeſt holde thus of Gods promyſes thorow fayth, and vſeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſpeare and ſhylde to defende thy ſelfe, and to ſmyte Satan, then out of the ſame it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth as the prophete ſayeth farther:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That thou nedeſt not to feare for the
<pb facs="tcp:4561:50"/>horrybleneſſe of the nyght,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the arowes that flye in the daye tyme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the peſtilence that commeth pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uely in the darke,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For ſyckeneſſe that deſtroyeth in the noone daye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For theſe foure aduerſites ſet forwarde and ſhorten the lyfe of the vnbeleuers: But the faythfull hath ſuch conſolacion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,<note place="margin">The hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribleneſſe of the nyghte.</note> that he nedeth not to be afrayed. Fyrſt for the horrybleneſſe of the nyght. That is, for all maner of tentacion and deceate, that happen vnto men by nyght in the darkneſſe. For thys we all perceaue, that in the nyght and in the darkneſſe, we are weaker mynded, of more deſpayre, and more afrayed then in the lyghte. The bloude runneth to oure har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; the heeres ſtonde vpryght, and all the body waxeth colde for feare. Out of thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we thynke we ſe, heare &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue ſomwhat, which in very dede is not ſo. Then goeth ther one aſtray, another leſeth hys coloure, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde falleth ſycke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourthe is become crocked, the fyfthe goeth out of hys wyt. And ſo men thynke, that the deuell hath done it, where as it is yet a playne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural workynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exceadynge grete feare, whyche wolde deſtroye a man euen by daye
<pb facs="tcp:4561:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>tyme, yf it were ſo greate.<note place="margin">The deuil is cauſe. of horry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe.</note> Howbeyt true it is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuell cauſeth ſuch feare, and pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it in, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye begile and deſtroye vs by feare, as by a naturall workynge: Yet is it nothynge but a feare. For the prophete cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it not an euel or good ſprete, but planely the horrybleneſſe of the nyght. Nother is it ony thynge els alſo but an horrour &amp; feare. and continueth an horrour and feare.</p>
                  <p>Therfore where a ryght belefe is, there is no feare. Where no fearfulneſſe is, there is alſo no horrour, nor fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſye of ſpretes, or deceatfulneſſe of the nyght,<note place="margin">The cauſe of lygte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges and ſuch lyke,</note> but playne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and boldneſſe. Yf onye thynge els be ſene (as fyre or lyghte,) they be but naturall thynges, out of the heate of the ground, lyke as lyghtenynges, draggons, fallyngeſtarres and cometes be in the ayre and in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But here wythall wyll not I ſpeake agaynſt the wouderfull viſions and tokens, whyche god ſendeth for a warnyng be for greate myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunces to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes in the daye tyme</note>Secondarely, is the faythfull ſure for the arowes that flye in the daye tyme. That is, all maner of myſchaunces which ouertake a man openly in the daye: and yet ſo ſodenly and vnwares, that he can not eſcape them. As whan a tyle falleth from the roofe of an houſe, whan a wycked beaſt doth euell, or
<pb facs="tcp:4561:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>whan an vngracious perſonne doth hurt in body, name, or good. For ſuche miſfortunes come for the mooſt perte ſo ſodenly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man can not preuente them, but muſt let them hyt as wyth an arowe, and afterward reſtore &amp; heale the harme wyth greate trauayle and la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure. But nowe wyll God preſerue hys faythfull from ſuch miſfortune, yf they haue hys promyſes before theyr eyes, beleue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and ordre theyr lyues therafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note>Thyrdly, a faythfull perſon nedeth not alſo to be afrayed for the peſtilence, that ſlyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth in preuely in the darke. Thys is verely a comfortable promyſe in thys daungerous tyme, for the whiche we ſhulde by ryght put oure truſt in God, and thanke him therfore, for aſmuch as it is one of the mooſt perlous and horryble plages, wherwyth he viſyteth and punyſſheth the ſynne of the worlde. For it taketh hold of lyfe vnwares, and plucketh a man awaye in two or thre dayes, (or euer he can ordre hys buſyneſſe and houſe, &amp; make hys teſtament) crepeth in preuely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> darke, ſo that no man knoweth what it is, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it commeth, or whyther it goeth: therfor can no man kepe hymſelfe ſurely from it.</p>
                  <p>For yf it were in meate or drynke, it myghte be eſchued: Yf it were an euell tayſt, it myght be expelled wyth a ſwete ſauoure:
<pb facs="tcp:4561:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Yf it were an euel wynde, the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre myghte wyth diligence be made cloſe therfore: Yf it were a cloude or myſt, it myght be ſene, and auoyded. Yf it were a rayne, a man myghte couer hym ſelfe for it. But now is it a ſecret myſfortune, that crepeth in preuely, ſo that it can nother be ſene nor herde, nother ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led nor tayſted tyll it haue done the harme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The more daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous the peſtilence is, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re excellent is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe.</note>Therfore the more daungerous and noyſome that the plage is, the better &amp; more excellent is the promyſe, that no man ſhulde haue cauſe to deſpayre: For how might God make vs a more excellent and fayrer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe, then that he promyſeth to delyuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peſtilence, vs that be hys chyldren, and that we nede not to be afrayed therof, though a thouſande dye of the ſame at oure left ſyde, and ten thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de at our ryght ſyde? Yet ſhall it not reach vnto vs, yf we do but beleue thys promyſe, and let it be oure ſpeare and ſhylde? For yf we ſo do, then ſhall ſuche poyſoned arowes eyther not hytte vs at all, or els not wounde vs to death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that deſtroyeth in the noo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne daye.</note>Fourthly, God wyll alſo preſerue hys chyldren from the ſyckneſſe that deſtroyeth in the noone daye: For the noone day (whan the Sonne is at the ſtrongeſt) is cauſe of muche heate and feuerous ſyckneſſe, ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in thoſe contryes, where the Sonne ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:4561:52"/>hye, and commeth nye ouer mens hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. For greate heate bryngeth much ſweate, conſumeth and altereth the bloude, cauſeth inordinate drynkynge, and maketh that the people are gladde to coole the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues agayne foolyſhly: Wherout then aryſe all maner of perlous diſeaſes, whyche be not very vnlyke the ſyckneſſe of the peſtilence.</p>
                  <p>Now whether it be feare of the nyght, or arowe of the daye: whether it be peſtilence or ſyckneſſe, that commetht by the euel South: wynde, or what plage it wyl that lyeth vpon the worlde becauſe of theyr ſynnes, God the LORDE wyll preſerue hys faythfull there from, or delyuer them from it: and that ſhall come to paſſe ſo certaynly and ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that (as the Prophete ſayeth) thoughe a thouſande fal at thy left ſyde, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de at thy ryghte ſyde, yet ſhal it not touche the. Thys is doutleſſe a louynge, mercifull, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable, and fayre promyſe, wheron oure hart by reaſon ſhulde truſte, and chefely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the ſame. For he that ſpeaketh it, is Almyghty and true: therfore ſhulde we by reaſon geue exedence vnto hym. For we can do God no greater dyſhonoure, then to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre in hys holy worde. We oughte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be much more afrayed of the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate feare, then of death it ſelfe: for death can
<pb facs="tcp:4561:52"/>not hurt vs, in aſmuch as we (thorowe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme) are grafted and buryed vnto like death with Chriſt.<note place="margin">Fearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth mooſt hurte</note> But fearfulneſſe (whych is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge els but an vnbelefe) maye harme vs, and brynge vs into imprudence. Wherfore my mooſt dearely beloued, take theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes to harte, ſtrength youre hart, mynde, and vnderſtandynge therewyth, and be not fayntharted. So ſhal ye proue by experience, that God is true, and faythfully perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that whyche he promyſeth.</p>
                  <p>And that ye maye the more eaſely beleue it, I wyll declare it vnto youre charite by a ſymilytude howe it commeth to paſſe, and whence it ſpryngeth, that a ryght faythfull Chriſten man can be ſo ſafe and fre from all theſe plages: For it is good to vnderſtande, and comfortable to knowe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of the darcke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the nyght.</note>Youre charyte ſeyth and proueth dayly by experience, howe myghtye &amp; horrible thynge the darkneſſe of the nyght is. For whan it falleth, it couereth all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the coloure and faſhion of all creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, captiuateth all men and beaſtes lyuyng, that they muſt be ſtyll and reſt, yee &amp; maketh them fayntharted and fearfull, and ſo of all thynges it is a myghty inuincible tyraunt, whom no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Neuertheleſſe it is not yet ſo myghtye, that it can darken,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:53"/>ouerwhelme, and quench the leaſt lyght that is founde in the worlde. For we ſe, that the darker the nyght is, the clearer do the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſhyne:<note place="margin">The can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle lyghte ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Yee the leeſt candle lyght that is lyghted, withſtandeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole nyght, &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth not onely the darkneſſe not to couer or oppreſſe it, but geueth lyght eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the darkneſſe, and ſmyteth it backe a certayne ſpace on euery ſyde: and thyther as it is borne, muſt darkneſſe depart, and geue place vnto the lyghte: all the power and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe therof, can not helpe agaynſt it.</p>
                  <p>And though a lyght be ſo weake, that it geueth not lyght farre aboute it, nother can ſmyte the darkneſſe abacke (as the ſparke of an whotecole) yet can not the darkneſſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, much leſſe to quenche it: but it geueth lyght it ſelfe alone, ſo that it maye be ſene a farre of in the darkneſſe, and remayneth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouercome of the ſame, though it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not helpe other thynges, nor geue lyght vnto them.</p>
                  <p>Yee (that yet more wonderfull is) a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhynynge pece of woode, whiche neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe hath the faynteſt lyghte that can be founde, remayneth inuincible of all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of darckneſſe: and the more it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed aboute wyth darckneſſe, the clearer lyght it geueth, ſo lytle can darckneſſe ouer come or hold downe ony lyght: but it ruleth
<pb facs="tcp:4561:53"/>vanquyſheth, and expelleth the darkeneſſe, whych els ouerwhelmeth, ſnareth, &amp; putteth all thynges in feare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of a ſprynge of a well</note>Euen ſo lykewyſe doth a well ſprynge alſo, for there maye we ſe, how a lytle vayne of water breaketh out of the grounde, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſcarce ſo great as a fynger. And whan it is cloſed in rounde aboute that the water maye gather together, and muſt nedes be a dych or a pyt, yet ſpryngeth it neuertheleſſe. And though the water be certayne hundreds weyght aboue the ſprynge, yet maye not it dryue the ſprynge backe, but the ſprynge dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the whole burthen of the water backe, and aboue it ſelfe, and ſpryngeth ſtyll more and more, tyll the pole flow ouer. And yf the other water be foule and vncleane, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not myxte it ſelfe vnder the freſhe clere water of the ſprynge, but it remayneth clere tyll it come farther abrode from the fyrſte heade therof, as it maye all be ſene wyth eyes, and alſo be proued by daylye experience.</p>
                  <p>Yf a naturall lyghte then be ſo mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye agaynſte the darkeneſſe of the nyghte, &amp; an earthen well ſprynge ſo ſtronge in ſtry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge agaynſt all ſtandynge waters: howe muche more doth it then the true euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge and heauenly lyght, and the onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyncible ſprynge of all lyfe, namely, God
<pb facs="tcp:4561:54"/>the LORDE oure maker and Sauioure?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">God is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> lyghte</note>That God is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true, euerlaſtynge and heauenly lyght, wytneſſeth Ihon the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt in the fyrſt Chapter, &amp; ſayeth: God was the worde, in hym was the lyfe, and the lyfe was the lyghte of men. Lykewyſe alſo in hys Canonicall epiſtle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt Chapter: God is lyght, and in hym is no darkneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">God is a quicke ſprynge.</note>In lyke maner, That he is the onely inuincyble ſprynge of all lyfe, wytneſſeth the prophete Ieremy in the ſeconde chapter For there ſayeth the LORDE: My people commytteth a dubble ſynne, they forſake me the lyuynge ſprynge of lyfe, and make them ſelues fayre welles, whyche neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe geue no water. And Dauid ſayeth in the .xxxv. Pſalme: Wyth the is the ſprynge of lyfe, and in thy lyght ſe we light.</p>
                  <p>Yf God the LORDE the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true lyght, it followeth, that all they which put theyr truſt in hym, be as a burnynge candle: for by fayth doth God dwell in our hartes, and we are the lyuynge te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God, as Paule to the Corinthians doth wytneſſe more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once. Therfore ſayeth Chriſte of hys diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Math. v. Ye are the lyght of the worlde And of Ihon the Baptyſte: He was a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge and ſhynynge lyght. Ioh. v. Lykewyſe yf God be the euerlaſtynge &amp; lyuynge foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:54"/>it followeth, that the faythfull be euen flowynge ſprynges. Therfore ſayeth Chriſt alſo, Ioh. vii. Who ſo beleueth on me as the ſcripture ſayeth, out of hys body ſhall flowe ſtreames of lyuyng water: But this he ſayd of the ſprete, whiche they that beleue on hym ſhulde receaue.</p>
                  <p>Lyke as the darkeneſſe of the nyght nowe can hurte no earthly or wordly lyght, but muſt geue place and flye from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght: Euen ſo Sathan alſo whyche is a prynce of ſpirytuall darkeneſſe, can do no harme to a true ryghte beleuyng Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but muſt feare and flye from hym: For God, whyche is the euerlaſtynge lyghte, dwelleth and ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in hys hart, and dryueth and expelleth farre from hym all the workes of darkneſſe. And lyke as no heape of water can dryue bache ony fountayne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grounde, and hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the quycke ſprynge therof, and lyke as no vnclenneſſe can make it foule: euen ſo alſo can no aduerſyte of this worlde take awaye or ſhorten ony Chriſten mans lyfe. For God whyche is the fountayne of all lyfe, dwelleth and lyueth in hys harte, &amp; dryueth all hurtfull poyſon and mortall ſyckneſſe farre awaye from thence, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> not only it can not harme hym, but he alſo helpeth other people, and delyuereth them by hys preſence:
<pb facs="tcp:4561:55"/>euen as a lyght that ſhyneth farre aboute it, and as a ſprynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alwaye floweth, runneth and maketh the grounde moyſt an frutefull.</p>
                  <p>And thys is it that the LORDE ſayeth in the Goſpell, in the laſt of Marke: The tokens that ſhall followe them whyche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, are theſe: In my name ſhall they caſt out deuels, ſpeake wyth new tunges, dryue away ſerpentes: &amp; yf they drynke ony dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye thynge, it ſhall not hurte them: They ſhall laye handes vpon the ſycke, and they ſhall recouer. So is it red alſo in the Actes of the Apoſtles the .v. Chapter, that the ſycke were made whole onely of ſaynt Peters ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow. So vtterly muſt vanyſhe euery thynge that is contrary and agaynſte the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge lyghte, and ſprynge of lyfe, where a ryght Chriſten man is, in whom God dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth by a true belefe, and out of whome the holy gooſt ſhyneth and floweth.</p>
                  <p>Let Sathan then preaſſe in here wyth all hys darkneſſe and wyth all hys hurtfull infection,<note place="margin">Satan is dryuen back by fayth</note> yet ſhall ye ſe in belefe, that he can not take nor deſtroye ony Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth yf he continue in fayth, and kepe God in hys harte: But he ſhalbe ſmytten backe and dryuen awaye by force, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wonderfull workes of Chriſte and of all ſayntes do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtly declare. Therfor is it a great ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:4561:55"/>for a Chriſten man to be ſo afrayed for the plage of the peſtilence,<note place="margin">It is a gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ate ſhame for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten man to feare the peſtilence</note> as to flye from them whome he is bounde to ſerue by Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. For by reaſon he ſhulde wyth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out al feare make haiſte vnto them, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to fulfyll Gods commaundemente, but alſo by hys preſence to helpe them, yf theyr fayth do els worke wyth all. But yf it come not to paſſe, yet is he ſure, for as much as God dwelleth in hym, and he walketh and goeth in Gods commaundement. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynly thys promyſe ſhall not fayle hym:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Though a thouſande fall at thy ſyde, and ten thouſande at thy ryght ſyde, yet ſhall it not touch the.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But wyth fayth muſt theſe wordes be taken holde vpon, for naturall reaſon doth not comprehende them, in as muche as in dede it appeareth farre otherwyſe. And no man nedeth to thynke nor iudge, that they whyche dye of thys plage, be all vnchriſten and faythleſſe: but we ought not to doute but that ther dye therof many vertuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and leaue many vngodly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Naturall death hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peneth two way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</note>Thys is done, becauſe that death maye happen to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two maner of wayes. One waye, after the commune courſe of nature, accordynge as euery mans death is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hym of God, and we haue conſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:4561:56"/>it in baptyme. Of thys ſayeth the prophet Iob in the .xiiii. Chapter. A man hath hys appoynted tyme, the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of hys monethes ſtandeth wyth the: thou haſt appoynted him hys boundes, whyche he ſhall not ouerpaſſe.</p>
                  <p>Another waye maye death happen to a man before the tyme, by reaſon of hys greate &amp; greuous ſynnes: As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE hath threa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tened by Moſes, that yf hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement be not kept, he wyll cauſe peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to reygne. Wherout it is certayne, that whan they be kepte, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plage abydeth out. Lykewyſe ſayeth he in the commaundementes: Honour father and mother that thou mayeſt lyuelonge, &amp;c. Out of the whyche it is certayne, that hys lyfe whyche doth them not,<note place="margin">Hys lyfe that ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not Gods com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes ſhalbe ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tened.</note> ſhalbe ſhortened. In lyke maner ſayeth Dauid in the .lv. Pſal. The bloud thyrſty ſhall not bryng theyr lyfe to the halfe nombre. Wherout it is ſure that they ſhulde lyue muche longer, yf they ſhed not innocent bloud. Lykewyſe ſayeth Chriſt Luce. xii. Yf ye do not repent, ye ſhall all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe, as they that the tower in Siloa fell vpon. Where by it is certayne, that who ſo repenteth not, maye loke for all myſfortune.</p>
                  <p>And of thys vntymely death onely ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thys Pſalme, and promyſeth the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſten men, that they ſhalbe fre from it. For from the ryght appoynted death into
<pb facs="tcp:4561:56"/>the whyche we haue conſented in baptyme, we can nor ſhalbe delyuered. Wherfore yf a vertuous ryghte Chriſten man dye of thys plage, it is certaynly hys very houre appoyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vnto hym of God, whyche he can not preuente. But doutleſſe ther dye of it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſynners alſo beſyde, whyche myghte well lyue longer yf they repented. And though ſome be taken becauſe of theyr ſynnes, yet be they not therfor damned: but yf they axe forgeueneſſe of ſynnes and beleue, they ſhall be ſaued. As Paule ſayeth: Whan we be iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged, we are chaſtened of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> LORDE, that we ſhulde not be condemned wyth the worlde.</p>
                  <p>Thus goeth it then together, that iuſte men dye theyr owne ryght death, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dye an vntymely death, and therwyth doth God punyſhe the worlde ſoreſt of all be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of theyr ſynnes, but ſpareth hys owne for theyr faythes ſake. Therfore ſhulde they not be fearful nor fayntharted, but (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete ſayeth) they ſhulde loke &amp; beholde, how the vngodly are recompenced: For whether the wycked dye before the tyme, or the iuſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghte ſeaſon, yet is it done both for the punyſhement and plage of the vngodly.<note place="margin">God puny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth men by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath of other.</note> Yf vertuous fathers &amp; mothers dye from wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dyſobedient chyldren, then be the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren plaged, for they are afterwarde euell
<pb facs="tcp:4561:57"/>nurtoured, hanged or ſlayn. Yf yonge chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dye from wycked fathers and mothers, then be the chyldren delyuered, &amp; the fathers and mothers punyſhed, in that they haue ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thered theyr goodes for thoſe that they wyſhe them not vnto. Yf tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes dye, then bethey punyſhed, and the perſecuted Chriſten dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. Yf good rulers dye, which wyth theyr wyſdome haue maynteyned peace and good gouernaunce, then be they in peace: And ſo the vngodly whyche are left alyue, rayſe vp warre and ſedicion, and be alwaye punyſhed worſe and worſe. Shortly who ſo hath eyes of fayth, ſeyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true beleuers dye in a ryght ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dye or lyue for theyr welth, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked for theyr punyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly before the tyme. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dye or lyue, it is done for theyr welthe. But whether the wycked dye or lyue, it is done for theyr punyſhment, and by all wayes ſhall they be plaged, and theyr wyckedneſſe ſhall be rewarded them.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore my mooſt derely beloued, take ye ſuch doctrine &amp; comforte to harte, and fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Flye in good earneſt (by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce &amp; amendement) from ſynne, wher wyth the world hath deſerued thys horryble plage: And flye by a true vpryght fayth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods word, wherin is the fountayne of lyfe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght of men: Then ſhall ye be whole and ſafe from thys and other plages, <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:4561:57"/>ſo lyue to the honoure of God and welth of your neghbour, tyll the appoynted tyme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, wherin God the father (in the death of Chriſt that we be baptiſed in) ſhal ſende for vs out of thys myſerable lyfe to hys owne euerlaſtynge kyngdome: Which God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs all. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Howe they ought to be comforted that are in bodyly ſyckneſſe or trouble.</head>
                  <p>DEarly beloued brother I truſte ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that all thynges, whether it be ſyck<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, anguyſhe, or what miſfortune ſo euer it be, it commeth all from almyghtye God. For yf he be your faythfull father,<note place="margin">Rom. viii All thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſerue for the beſte vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue God.</note> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth he it to your furtheraunce that he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth holde on your olde Adam, and leadeth hym preſoner wyth thys bonde of your ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and helpeth you to tame and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfy hym, that ſo ye maye yelde youre ſelfe the better vnto your LORDE God, and hange on the croſſe wyth Chriſte. For thys cauſe is ſuche ſyckneſſe of yours a fatherly chaſtenynge: For whome God loueth,<note place="margin">Heb. xii.</note> hym doth he chaſten. And of hys fatherly mercy
<pb facs="tcp:4561:58"/>taketh he thus holde vpon you wyth very truthe and loue. Happely he ſeyth that your olde Adam wyll be to wanton and raſh for you, and waxeth to ſtronge &amp; fearce for you. And for thys cauſe putteth the LORDE a brydle into hys mouth, whereby he be not hurtfull vnts your noble ſoule and myſcary her. Fleſh and bloude is ſtronger in you tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſprete, therfore helpeth he your ſprete to fyghte. Perchaunce yf ye were whole, it myghte entyce you to ſynne agaynſte God, whereby hys holy name myghte be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſo were youre ſoule the more curſed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fylthyneſſe of manyfolde ſynnes. But nowe doth he auoyde all that from you tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row fatherly mercy, and turneth awaye youre fleſh and bloude that alwaye rageth agaynſte the ſprete,<note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> and leadeth it captiue, ſo that it hath no more rowme nor occaſion to couet all maner of ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>Seynge than that hys fatherly wyll is ſuche, and that ſuche thynges do happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you to good, therfore do I earneſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſh you that by no meanes ye do wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande hys fatherly wyll, but praye hartely, that hys wyll be done and fulfylled in you vnto hys prayſe. And hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeke to graunte you his mercy, tha tye may beare thys croſſe of hys paciently:<note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> For pacience bryngeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,
<pb facs="tcp:4561:58"/>experience bryngeth hope, but hope letteth vs not come to confuſion. Thus haue ye nowe occaſion to be paciente, and wyllyngly to ſuffre al maner of thynge that God ſendeth vnto you, for ſo muche as ye perceaue in your harte, that he meaneth the thynge in very dede, and thys commeth by tryenge. For wythout ye aſſaye it wyth the dede how good it is ſo to retayne the LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE, (as Dauid ſayeth:<note place="margin">Pſal. c. xviii. i.</note> It is good to my that I haue ben in trouble, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye learne thy ryghteouſneſſes) ye can not hope and truſte in hym: In ſo muche as ye haue not aſſayed that ſuch fatherly loue is hyd vnder thys rodde.</p>
                  <p>But whan ye haue perceaued ſuche a thynge, than are ye bolde in all ſufferynge, and take hope vnto you, the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger the more: ſeynge God doth ſo truely aſſiſte you. And though he do let you ſyncke a lytle whyle &amp; ſtyck faſte, yet doth he drawe you forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, though it be longe. He ſuffreth you a lytle to ſwymme and to douke, but not to drowne. Wherby ye maye perceaue that he wyll neuer forſake you, whyche hath ſo ofte and many tymes ayded you. Yf he doth brynge you ſometyme in greate anguyſhe,<note place="margin">Dan. xiiii.</note> ſo that ye myght thynke it all to be done wyth you, yet forſake hym not, but let your truſt
<pb facs="tcp:4561:59"/>and hope remayne faſte and ſure in hym: for ye haue heretofore learned well ynough the propertye and nature home he goeth aboute wyth hys: ye knowe alſo that it is not done of anger or hate, but of pure and entier loue. Abyde therfore for the LORDE in all your ſufferynge, and truſte wholy and inceaſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in his mercy and helpe, how longe ſo euer he wythdraweth hymſelfe and taryeth: And be fully perſuaded that thys your ſyckneſſe, (or ſuche other grefe) is not vnto death,<note place="margin">Ioh. ix. xi.</note> but for the honoure of God, and your profyte &amp; ſaluacion. For who ſo darre truſte ſo in God, and beleue his promyſes ſtedfaſtly, the ſame ſhall neuer dye, as Chriſte hymſelfe ſayeth: Yee and byndeth it alſo wyth an oth that it be ſo in dede,<note place="margin">Ioh. viii</note> ſayenge: Verely verely I ſaye vnto you: Yf ony man kepe my word, he ſhall neuer ſe death. And in another place ſayeth Chriſte:<note place="margin">Ioh. xi</note> I am the reſurrection and the lyfe. He that beleueth on me, ſhall lyue, though he were deade already: and who ſo euer lyueth &amp; beleueth on me, ſhall neuer dye.</p>
                  <p>Kepe and holde ſure thys comforte, and be bolde there vpon. For who ſo beleueth in Chriſte, ſhall not tayſte of death, but is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſſed from death to lyfe. Euen as he wytneſſeth of hymſelfe, where he ſayeth: Who ſo beleueth on me,<note place="margin">Ioh. v</note> hath euerlaſtynge
<pb facs="tcp:4561:59"/>lyfe. But thys is the lyfe euerlaſtynge:<note place="margin">Ioh. xvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> that they knowe the, that thou only arte the true God, &amp; whom thou haſt ſente Ieſus Chriſt. The lyfe euerlaſtyng begynneth here in this lyfe, &amp; e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dureth euer. For who ſo hath Chriſt, theſame truely hath very lyfe: for he hym ſelfe is the lyfe. Ioh. xv. He is alſo the truth. What ſo euer he promyſeth you, that ſhalbe yee, and not naye. He wyl abyde faſte by his promyſe, euen as he ſayeth hymſelfe: I will not take away my kyndneſſe from hym,<note place="margin">Pſal. lxxxviii.</note> nor ſuffre my truth to fayle. I wyl not breake my conuenaunte not diſanulle the thynge that is gone out of my lyppes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Howe wyfe chyldren and other frendes ſhalbe comforted, the huſbonde beynge dead.</head>
                  <p>SEynge nowe that God hath called your huſbonde, father or other good frende out of thys myſery into euerlastynge ioye, therfore ſhall ye receaue it wyllyngly: for it is hys worke. Repyne not therfore at hys worke, nother wepe agaynſt his wyl, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe vnto him, take it of his hande as a fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therly prouynge, &amp; ſaye with Iobe God hath
<pb facs="tcp:4561:60"/>geuen vs hym, &amp; hath taken hym agayn, the name of LORDE be bleſſed: as it was the LORDES wyll, ſo is it happened.</p>
                  <p>God almyghty wyll proue you as be dyd Iob how ye wyll behaue youre ſelfe as he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out of youre ſyght the thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye loue. He wyll admytte well ynough y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye be ſorye. For it is ſeldome ſene but a man (be he neuer ſo vyle,<note place="margin">Ther is no membre of the body but it hath hys proper gyfte.</note> or of ſo lytle reputacion) hath euer a ſondery gyfte wherew<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſerued &amp; profyted other. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame gyftes were not greatly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garded in a man whyle he lyued: for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly we regarde lytle ſuche thynges as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: but as ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man is gone, ſo ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> veſſel is ſpilte, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begynne we to want the gyftes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned therin. Therfore is it no maruayle that we be ſory for ſuche a gyfte of God, yf it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of our ſyghte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">God is diſpleaſed wyth myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſynge of hys gyftes</note>As longe as we uſe men &amp; the gyftes accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng as they be ordeyned of God for our ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſite, than do we well, and that can God ſuffre well ynough: But that we miſvſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and make an ydoſt of them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can not God ſuffre. For whan we put oure truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte in man, or ony other creature, than do we wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gge, &amp; miſvſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, and the curſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs wherof it is wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ierem. xvii. Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that putteth hys truſt in man.</p>
                  <p>For all mans helpe is to be ſuffred only
<pb facs="tcp:4561:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be preſente, and that we haue nede of them: but as ſoone as they are gone, than muſt we loke for other helpe, namely: God, lettynge go it that paſſeth awaye, thynkyng it to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, faydynge at the twynklynge of an eye, and vanyte that is in thys world. We haue here no abydynge thyng, but muſt loke aboute for the thynge to come that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">God can not abyde that we make much of creatures</note>For thys cauſe doth God draw &amp; pull vs ſo from the creatures. And ſeynge he is oure true father, bridegrome &amp; huſbo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, he can not (for he is ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge &amp; gelous) abyde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſet oure hope, loue, or truſt vpon ony creatur. Thys is the cauſe then that he doth take vs from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and caryeth vs vpon hym ſelfe. For loke on what creature we haue mooſte hope, loue, and affection, that wyll he ſooneſt take out of ſyght, yf he doth loue vs. And whan he hath ſuche gelouſy vpon vs, than doth he mooſte chefely declare hys loue towarde vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">We ought to call noman father vy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> earth.</note>By thys alſo it commeth that Chriſte Mathe .xviii. forbyddeth vs to call ony man father vpon earth, for we haue onely one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen, namely God, which wyl nor can ſuffre vs to call or to haue ony ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon earth father: &amp; that becauſe we ſhulde depend and hange only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, lokyng for al good of hym. For he wyll be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame that we maye
<pb facs="tcp:4561:61"/>hardely truſte vnto: ſeynge he can not, nor wyll fayle vs, &amp; that becauſe he is no earthly but an heauenly father. For thys cauſe than is that man bleſſed and happy, that putteth hys truſt, hope, and confidence in the LOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DE, as the prophete ſayeth. Pſal. xxxiii.</p>
                  <p>Fynally yf whan nature fulfylleth hyr courſe,<note place="margin">Iob. xiii</note> man hath but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual trauayl &amp; my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, &amp; after that thys courſe of nature is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; at reſt, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is eaſed of ſo great trauayl: we ſeme to hate rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to loue them that be departed yf we wold wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in this wretched worlde agayne. Moreouer in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng ſo muche of oure frendes departed, and ſettyng ſo greate affection vpon them, wyſh ynge Gods worke not to be fulfylled vpon them, we blame God in hys wyll and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge: as though he knew not better what were beſt both for them and vs, than we.</p>
                  <p>Let vs therfore ſet oure wyll in Gods wyll, and ſuffer hym to worke at hys plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. For he knoweth beſt what is both oure frendes and oure ſoules health.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ Printed in Southwarke by me Iames Nicolſon.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4561:61"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
